<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lot's little one. Or Meditations on Gen. 19. vers. 20 Being the substance of severall sermons sometimes delivered by William Ince Mr in Arts, late senior fellow of Trinitie Colledge Dublin. Published since his death, by R.I.</title>
            <author>Ince, William, d. 1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03966</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854511</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03966)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 991:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lot's little one. Or Meditations on Gen. 19. vers. 20 Being the substance of severall sermons sometimes delivered by William Ince Mr in Arts, late senior fellow of Trinitie Colledge Dublin. Published since his death, by R.I.</title>
                  <author>Ince, William, d. 1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. R[aworth] for the kingdom of Ireland, and are to be sold by Iohn Crook and Richard Sergier, in Dublin, at the signe of St Austin in Castle-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Randulphus Ince.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Engraved title page dated 1641.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; A1, engraved title page, lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XIX, 18-20 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19937:1"/>
            <p>LOT'S LITTLE ONE OR MEDITATIONS ON GEN. 19. VERS. 20. Being the ſubſtance of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall SERMONS ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times delivered By WILLIAM INCE M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> in Arts, late Senior Fellow of <hi>Trinitie</hi> Colledge <hi>Dublin.</hi> Publiſhed ſince his death, by <hi>R. I.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 5. 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whoſoever ſhall breake one of theſe <hi>leaſt</hi> Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſhall teach men ſo, he ſhall be called the <hi>leaſt</hi> in the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>I. R.</hi> for the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Crook</hi> and <hi>Richard Sergier,</hi> in <hi>Dublin,</hi> at the Signe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> in Caſtle-ſtreet. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:19937:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur Tho. Wykes. August <hi>26. 1640.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19937:2"/>
            <p>Reverendiſſimo in Chriſto Patri LANCELO TO, Providentiâ divinâ D<hi rend="sup">•o</hi> Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epiſcopo <hi>Dublinienſi</hi> Hiberniae Primati &amp; Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litae, Has, fratris chariſſimi <hi>Gulielmi Ince,</hi> in artibus magiſtri, Colegii Sanctae <hi>Trinitatis Dublin</hi> nuper ſocii ſenioris, lucubrationes poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humas, igni ab authore devotas, è Sybillinis veluti foliis (ut plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimum) collectas, amore &amp; curâ fraternis, luce &amp; corpore donatas, in meritiſſimae, Tam authoris dum viveret, quam fratris ſuperſtitis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervantiae teſtimonium, L. M. D. D. D. Clementiae veſtrae ſervus à ſacris addictiſſimus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Randulphus Ince.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="biblical_source_text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19937:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19937:3"/>
            <head>The Text.</head>
            <head type="sub">GEN. 19. VERS.</head>
            <p n="18">18. ET dixit <hi>Lot</hi> ad eos, ô ne ſic quaeſo Domine mi.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Ecce nune invenit ſervus tuus gratiam in conſpectu tuo, &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificaſti miſericordiam tuam erga me, ſervando vitam meam, &amp; ego non potero liberare me ad montem, ne fortè aliquod malum capiat &amp; moriar.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Eccenunc civitas ista propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua ad fugiendum illuc, &amp; ipſa exigua eſt, eripiam me nunc illuc, (nonne exigua eſt?) &amp; vivet ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mea.</p>
            <p n="18">18. ANd <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid unto them, ô not ſo my Lord.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Bebold now thy ſervant hath
<pb facs="tcp:19937:4"/>found grace in thy ſight, and thou haſt magnified thy mercy, which thou haſt ſhewed unto me in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my life, and I cannot eſcape to the mountaine, leaſt ſome evill take me and I dye.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Behold now this Citie is near to flee unto, and it is a little one, ô let me eſcape thither (is it not a little one?) and my Soul ſhall live.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19937:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 19. VERS. 18, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid unto them, O not ſo my Lord, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are a part of a prayer, that prayer of a ſtory, a ſtory almoſt as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable as any, that was ever yet left upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord ſince the creation of man, and that is the deſtruction of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> upon which God indeed commanded the <hi>wife of</hi> Lot <hi>not to look back,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> and her hard heart of unbelief and diſobedience <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed her into a pillar</hi> of ſtone; ſo that ſhe, that on Gods bidding would not goe, when ſhe would, ſhould now ſtand, ſtand an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19937:5"/>monument of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt the <hi>children of diſobedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it not awaken your won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that where the Text ſayes a <hi>Pillar of Salt,</hi> I ſay of Stone. It is conſonant to reaſon, and the generall voyce of interpreters, that it was Salt rather, <hi>quoad ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem, quam naturam ſpecific am,</hi> rather in reſemblance of the graine then identitie of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: elſe would it never have laſted through ſo many ages and yeers to <hi>Ioſephus</hi> his time,<note place="margin">Ioſephus. Antiquit. Iud. lib. <hi>11.</hi> nam extat. (inquit) ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die quoque.</note> who tels us that in his time there was <hi>ſtill extant ſuch a Stone,</hi> which tradition gave out to be this though then of one Stone it was become two monuments, one of Gods anger againſt the Wife of <hi>Lot,</hi> and the ſecond of Times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring teeth, which had delt with this as with many other monuments, whoſe antiquitie we reade by not reading them, and gueſſe at their age and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19937:5"/>by our neither reading nor underſtanding of them.</p>
            <p>But of this, we are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſhe was puniſhed for diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying, and her diſobedience was in <hi>looking back towards So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> when God had forbidden her.<note place="margin">Luk. 17. 32.</note> But what was to her forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den is to us commanded <hi>to look back upon Sodom.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All judgements are more for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like example then private revenge, and whatſoever was written,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 4.</note> 
               <hi>was written for our inſtruction.</hi> Yea and ſure by the qualitie of the judgement, God meant it for publike notice, and therefore God ſent a <hi>flaming judgement,</hi> that all eyes might ſee it, and by the light of it reade his juſt and fearefull indignation againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinners: <hi>a flaming judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> that it might be the world's <hi>Beacon</hi> to rouze and ſtartle ſnor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſecuritie, to awaken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and deteſtation of ſin: <hi>a flaming judgement,</hi> that men in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19937:6"/>this might ſee a glimce of hell, and in this temporarie foreſee, and foreſeeing feare, and fearing prevent another which is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
            <p>Look then back yee penitent and weeping ſoules, and judge whether is better, to be bathing in thoſe teares, or frying in thoſe flames.</p>
            <p>Look back impenitent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentleſſe wretches, and let your hearts (frozen in the Lees and and Dregs of ſinne) melt and thaw at thoſe flames, and let the horror of ſo prodigious a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, work the like effect on you, as on the <hi>Wife of</hi> Lot <hi>to transforme you,</hi> that it may be true of you, which was of <hi>Nabal,</hi> at the tydings of his wife <hi>Abgail,</hi> that <hi>his heart dyed within him and became as a Stone.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 37.</note> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 37.</p>
            <p>Look then back and behold prodigions ſinne requited with prodigious puniſhment; unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall luſt kindled with the fire
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19937:6"/>of hell, puniſhed with fire that againſt nature <hi>rained from heaven.</hi> In this behold the <hi>ſeverity of God:</hi> with no leſſe wonder behold his <hi>Mercy.</hi> Though for one righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mans ſake, he will not ſpare <hi>Sodom,</hi> yet for <hi>Sodom</hi> will be not deſtroy one righteous man. In this Citie, which was all chaffe and therefore fit fewell for the fire, there was but one ſheafe the familie of <hi>Lot,</hi> yet God will not deſtroy that,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.12.</note> but graciouſly as he promiſeth in his holy <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſends his Angels to hinde it together and lay it in the Garner of ſafety, when he burnes the chaffe with fire unquenchable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold the <hi>riches of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> he might without the leaſt taxe of his juſtice have deſtroyed <hi>Lot,</hi> who was not ſo righteous but God might have beheld mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of anger in him. He can never want in mans wickedneſſe a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage and defence of his own juſtice, and though he cannot
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19937:7"/>finde in the worſt of men ſo much goodneſſe as may merit the leaſt bleſſing; yet he cannot miſſe to finde in the beſt of men ſo much evill as may merit the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding that good God which is never exceptiouſly apprehenſive of mans infirmitie, nor uſes the advantage of our weakneſſe to ſhew the greatneſſe of his power in puniſhing but mercy in delivering: yea though <hi>he</hi> (I ſay) doe ſometimes make his temporarie judgements (like his common favours <hi>the Sunne and raine</hi>) <hi>to fall</hi> with equall indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie <hi>on the juſt and unjuſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.45.</note> yet more often and that eſpecially in notorious and exemplary judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the good mans ſingular pietie ſhall finde a ſingular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: and when wrath and judgement (like an univerſall deluge) ſhall ſweepe away a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nay a world of wicked men, God ſhall build the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19937:7"/>an Arke of ſafety: and he that like the Widowed Turtle ſingly mourned when all elſe generally rejoyced in the <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin,</hi> ſhall when all howle in the bitterneſſe of torment, ſingly rejoyce for his owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular deliverance.</p>
            <p>A voyce was heard (as <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> tels us) <hi>Audita major humanae vox,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit. hiſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>excedere Deos.</hi> Here was more then a <hi>voyce,</hi> the preſence of <hi>Angels,</hi> more then their <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> a <hi>zealous fervour and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe,</hi> more then an <hi>earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a ſacred violence to ſave</hi> Lot. <hi>While he lingred</hi> (ſaith <hi>verſ.</hi> 16.) <hi>the men laid hold upon his hand, and upon the hand of his wife, and upon the hand of his two daughters, the Lord being mercifull unto him, and they brought him forth and ſet him without the Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>And it came to paſſe when they had brought him forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that he ſaid, Eſcape for thy life, look not behinde thee, neither
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19937:8"/>ſtay thou in all the plaine: eſcape to the mountaine leaſt thou be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.</hi> Where come in the words of my text; <hi>And</hi> Lot <hi>ſaid unto them, ô not ſo my Lord: Behold now thy ſervant hath found grace in thy ſigh, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words then you ſee are a prayer, in which obſerve the two naturall parts of every prayer, <hi>thankeſgiving</hi> and <hi>petition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Thankeſgiving</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Behold now thy ſervant hath found grace in thy ſight, and thou hast magnified thy mercie, which thou haſt ſhewed unto me in ſaving of my life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Petition</hi> in the reſt of the words.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>thankeſgiving</hi> obſerve.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt the <hi>order</hi> of it.</item>
               <item>Secondly the <hi>matter</hi> of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt the <hi>order,</hi> that he makes the former ſence of Gods ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent favour, the firſt and beſt argument to obtain a ſubſequent requeſt; Be pleaſed to learne an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19937:8"/>holy policie;</p>
            <p>That gratitude is the beſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to a requeſt, and a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acknowledgement of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour received, the beſt way to obtaine another deſired.</p>
            <p>We ſend forth our prayers, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes as <hi>Noab bis Dove,</hi> and both returne emptie;<note place="margin">Gen. 8.9.</note> the <hi>Dove</hi> becauſe all the earth was covered with water, and <hi>our prayers</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all former favours are drowned in our forgetfulneſſe and ingratitude. We are ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with the immoderate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the things we want, that uſually we forget what we have.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Odioſum ſanè hominum genus officia exprobrantium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Citero,</note> 
               <hi>qua</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cicero</hi>) <hi>commemorare debet is in quem collata ſunt, non commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare qui contulit.</hi> The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of curteſies done, ſounds odiouſly in the mouth of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but gracefully becomes the mouth of the receiver, and to a free ingenuous nature ſhall not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19937:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>onely not be a check, that it ſhall prove a ſpur to a ſecond bounty.</p>
            <p>I might here then in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Lot's</hi> example, be bold to reprove the cuſtomary formes of many mens prayers, in which <hi>petition</hi> ingroſſes the whole length of their prayers and ſtrength of their devotion, while they (either as no part) exclude <hi>thankeſgiving,</hi> or (as to a leſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary part) give it the laſt and leaſt place, even the expiration of their zeale and prayer. Yet thus it is that like <hi>the daughters of the horſe-leech:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30.50.</note> we are ſtill cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>give, give;</hi> or like the Gud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons ever gaping to be fed, but our food obtain'd, ſtops our mouthes; not a word heard in way of thankfulneſſe. As if the things which were worth ſo much importunitie when reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, were not worth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement when obtained.</p>
            <p>But from the <hi>order</hi> of his thank. I come to the <hi>matter</hi> of it,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19937:9"/>in which obſerve theſe 4 parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A gift beſtowed, <hi>life.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The ſubject or object on whom, <hi>righteous Lot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The impulſive or moving cauſe, <hi>grace and mercie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The quantitie or extent of that mercie, <hi>great,</hi> in this word <hi>magnified.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>A temporall bleſſing, <hi>life,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on a <hi>righteous man;</hi> yet Gods great <hi>grace and mercie</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be the onely cauſe, yeilds us this concluſion;</p>
            <p>That even temporary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings beſtowed on the beſt of men, are of Gods free grace and great mercie, and not at all of mans merit. Or briefly,</p>
            <p>The beſt of men cannot merit the worſt of bleſſings. I might eaſily prove it, and as eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the ſaucie boldneſſe of thoſe <hi>Romiſh dreamers,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Ladder of Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> (whoſe humanitie ſtood on earth and his divinitie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19937:10"/>unto heaven) have found another ladder, even of their owne merits: a ladder that hath not onely <hi>perfection of parts but of degrees too,</hi> degrees by which they can climbe heaven. Such a one that good <hi>Patriarch never ſaw,</hi> never dream'd of, <hi>neper ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium quidem.</hi> Nor we need we indeed a better argument againſt them then their owne arrogance, which doth alwayes beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt it ſelf, and proves thoſe things wanting which it brags to be owner of.<note place="margin">Luk. 18.11.</note> Let theſe <hi>Phariſees</hi> then vaunt themſelves to be higher and neerer heaven then other men, but it may well be thought that rather the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their opinion, then reall and ſolide truth lifts them up to this height, that they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves higheſt, neereſt heaven,<note place="margin">Pſal. 138.6.</note> yet <hi>God that is in heaven beholdeth them a farre off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us rather imitate the humilitie of the truly good man,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19937:10"/>whoſe prayers are ſo farre from that odious <hi>theam</hi> of aſſuming merit, that none ſo much, none ſo frequent in imploring mercy.</p>
            <p>But this point being <hi>Polemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> let me leave it to the <hi>Lords worthies,</hi> and haſt to the ſecond part of my text, <hi>Lots petition,</hi> which is;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt Negative, <hi>ô not ſo my Lord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Secondly Affirmative, <hi>ô let me eſcape thither,</hi> that is to <hi>Zoar:</hi> either part backed with a ſeeming ſhew and ſtrength of reaſon. Firſt of the <hi>Negative.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And the reaſon of that is <hi>à difficultate conditionis praeſcriptae,</hi> the difficultie of the task impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>I cannot;</hi> proved by a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillogiſme, Ne fortè aliquod malum capiat &amp; moriar, least ſome evill take me and I dye. Evill</hi> behinde me, before me, with me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde me from <hi>Sodom,</hi> before me, in the diſconſolate ſolitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an unfrequented moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19937:11"/>in ſolitarineſs no company, or company worſe then beaſts or men: leaſt I be devoured by wilde beaſts, or rob'd by theeves who are wilde men: or if I be ſecure from the danger of fire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde me, of the mountaine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, yet I cannot for the evill with me, the length of the way, therefore <hi>I cannot eſcape to the mountaine, ne fortè aliquod malum capiat &amp; moriar, leaſt ſome evill take me and I dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next followes the Affirmative requeſt, where obſerve.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt the <hi>order of it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Secondly the <hi>matter of it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>order,</hi> that it comes in under the Lee and ſhelter of his arguments, and is ſet downe in a cloſe and <hi>Cryphick method,</hi> as though indeed it came in by a ſtrong and undoubted conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and rather by way of a neceſſary concluſion then an humble petition. <hi>Behold now.</hi> (ſayes <hi>Lot</hi>) <hi>this Citie, &amp;c. O let
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19937:11"/>me eſcape thither, viz.</hi> to <hi>Zoar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Lots</hi> Arguments to enforce his requeſt are, 1. <hi>à re,</hi> and 2. ae <hi>perſonâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the thing requeſted or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the requeſter himſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Are,</hi> from the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted, and that, firſt <hi>qualitate,</hi> the qualitie of it, ſecondly <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titate,</hi> the quantitie of it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt <hi>qualitate,</hi> and for qualitie <hi>its a Citie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Secondly <hi>quantitate</hi> the quantitie and that, firſt <hi>Viae,</hi> or ſecondly <hi>Termini.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Viae,</hi> for the quantitie of the way, <hi>it is neer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Termini, tis little:</hi> And now having ſent before theſe Arguments as <hi>Iacob bis three bands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen 32.19 and 31.</note> to mediate for the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his requeſt, heere fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the petition it ſelf like <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob halting:</hi> and needs muſt it halt, that in a worſe manner wreſtles with, nay againſt God in an unlawfull requeſt; <hi>Oreci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19937:12"/>me illuc, O let me eſcape thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: nonne parvula eft? is it not a little one?</hi> The ſame Argument by an Elegant <hi>Epanalepſis</hi> and <hi>interrogation</hi> againe repeated, as though he repoſed a great deale of confidence in the ſmalneſſe of the Citie, and by ſo eaſie, ſo facile a requeſt, would challenge God (as it were) of unkindneſſe, to deny him ſo poore a boone as a <hi>little one,</hi> yet of great and maine conſequence, as much as my life and ſafety is worth, <hi>and my ſoule ſhall live,</hi> which is</item>
            </list>
            <p>The laſt Argument from him ſelfe requeſting, <hi>my ſoule ſhall live,</hi> which may have a double meaning, either in oppoſition to the danger of the <hi>mountaine,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, in the <hi>mountaine</hi> my life is many wayes hazzarded, but in this <hi>Citie</hi> it is ſecured: or it may be expounded of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent here, <hi>my ſoule ſhall live,</hi> it will be a favor which will afford me much content and felicitie.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19937:12"/>
            <p>Thus having as <hi>Dido</hi> with her Oxe-hide,<note place="margin">Virgil.</note> cut the words into pieces, I have incloſed a large and ſpacious ground, wherein I intend (by Gods aſſiſtance) to build my enſuing diſcourſe, and firſt of the <hi>Negative petition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O not ſo my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Angels (as you may reade before <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16.) had wreſtled with <hi>Lot's</hi> dulneſſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.16.</note> and with a ſacred violence of love and mercy <hi>carried</hi> Lot <hi>and ſet him without the Gates of</hi> Sodom, there bid him and them with him <hi>eſcape to the mountaine and live.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Timor adde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret alas.</note> You might imagine that feare (if his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence halted) would lend him wings to flye to the mountaine, that his danger might have made him have treſpaſſed againſt his good manners, to have begun his journey before the Angel ended his ſpeech.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid ſtatis? nolunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Sat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>atquilicet eſſe beatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold a new delay from his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19937:13"/>unwillingneſſe, a new dialogue and direction from his better wiſedome!<note place="margin">Quid cauſae est merito, quinillis Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter ambas Iratus inflet buccas, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſe fore poſthac Tam facilem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, votis ut praebeat aurem? <hi>Horat.</hi> ibid.</note> 
               <hi>O not unto the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine—quid cauſae eſt merito? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How juſtly might God ceaſe to ſtrive with him, and let him periſh, who would thus contend againſt his own ſafety? But God that is of infinite mercie, will deſcend to mans owne conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for mans owne ſafety.</p>
            <p>Rather then <hi>Lot</hi> ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, the ſtrength of <hi>God</hi> will be overcome by mans weakneſſe, <hi>His</hi> wiſedome be directed by mans folly: nay rather then <hi>Lot</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, <hi>God</hi> will uſe a loving violence, nay will even ſuffer violence, let his owne command be violated, mans will be eſtabliſhed. <hi>Lot</hi> ſhall doe what he will, ſo he will be ſaved, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe <hi>God</hi> any conditions; make <hi>God</hi> remit of his Iuſtice againſt them of <hi>Zoar,</hi> which <hi>He</hi> would have deſtroyed, that <hi>He</hi> may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19937:13"/>extend his mercie to <hi>Lot,</hi> whom <hi>He</hi> will ſave.</p>
            <p>But this mercie of <hi>God</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more naturally to the verſe where the Angel even to the wonder of patience <hi>accepts him even concerning this request alſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.21.</note> I will therefore no longer inſiſt upon it, but onely make the Act of Gods mercie, lead me to the object of it mans perverſeneſſe, in <hi>Lots</hi> reply, <hi>One ſic quaeſo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine mi, O not ſo my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man's a froward and perverſe creature, one whom nothing can pleaſe, one whom any thing can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but diſpleaſe: that can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther want his wiſhes with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor enjoy them with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, but with equall repining and diſcontent both expects and attaines; in all varietie of his deſires being ever conſtant in his old diſlike, and the beginning of new wiſhes. It muſt be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a patience no leſſe then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite that can beare with his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19937:14"/>petulancie and folly. How diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietly doth he tumble and toſſe, like the troubled Sea, with every winde of report? every whiſper of danger diſquiets him, and plowes up the levell of his peace unto the furrowed wrinkles of forrow and diſcontent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> in his firſt Creation went through all the creatures, and looking upon each <hi>Species</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>ſaw that they were good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note> 
               <hi>Man</hi> in his corruption lookes upon all the creatures, and ſees ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is bad in them. <hi>Adam</hi> had a divine knowledge <hi>to name all the creatures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.20.</note> we ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> a diabolicall knowledge to nickname all the creatures. All our skill is become like the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe latter times <hi>meere Criticiſme,</hi> ſo that in this faire volumne of creation, in every claſſe of the creatures, where we might behold <hi>digitum Dei,</hi> the hand of <hi>God</hi> pointing at ſome curious text, that volumne have
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19937:14"/>we fild with our owne <hi>Asteriskes</hi> and <hi>Errata's,</hi> and where a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did cenſure might of every thing make a good conſtruction and take all in a faire ſence, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignitie of our wit will alter it with ſome idle conjecture, and though to the fulleſt period ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a—<hi>nonnulla deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There have been, and I doubt are yet ſome of <hi>Plinie</hi> his Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, who would be <hi>Gods teachers,</hi> who had they been preſent when <hi>God</hi> was creating the world, could have corrected the divine <hi>Ideas,</hi> and taught him how to have made all things in better number, order and meaſure.</p>
            <p>Since our firſt parents taſting the <hi>forbidden fruit;</hi> we their off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring diſtaſt the beſt things. The devill then promiſed a deitie for eating, and indeed we can <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri Deum,</hi> we have a mock-di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, that let <hi>God</hi> make what he will with never ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſſe,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19937:15"/>we can finde a fault with it; ſpeak the moſt plaine and powerfull truth, we can queſtion it: deale never ſo juſtly, we can taxe him for it: never ſo mercifully we can diſtaſt it: like <hi>Lucian's Momus</hi> that being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to judge of the excellence of thoſe maſter-peeces which the Gods made,<note place="margin">Lucian.</note> an horſe, an houſe, and a man, found fault with all three: that the horſe had not hornes, the houſe motion, and the man a window to look into his breaſt.</p>
            <p>As in the creation, ſo in the whole courſe of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, all Gods actions fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cenſure of mans froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.<note place="margin">Non etenim cunctis plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat vel Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter ipſe, Nec mittens pluviam nec cohibens plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viam. <hi>Prov. Graec.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether it raine or not, all are not content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis even a taske of divinitie to pleaſe man; not that this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19937:15"/>argues any weakneſſe in <hi>Gods</hi> power, who can doe all things, but a wickedneſſe in mans nature that will be pleaſed with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Not only the harder por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of afflicton, but even the beſt of his favours we entertaine with ſome diſlike, and <hi>Criticiſe</hi> with a froward curioſitie upon the choyceſt of his favours. Nay if <hi>God</hi> ſhould give us all things in the world, and not content over and beſide all, all would be as nothing, but ſo farre from ſatiating the unlimited deſire of mans appetite, or ſetling his thoughts in a quiet comp ſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that they would prove but a varietie of vexation to him, he would be pinched in that plentie, and ſtarv'd in that varietie: yea when God had done all to pleaſe him, he ſhould heare the voyce of his diſcontent ſcreaking in that harſh and unpleaſing note, <hi>O ne ſic quae ſo Domine mi, O, not ſo my Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19937:16"/>
            <p>It is an opinion of the <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goreans &amp; Platoniſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſto. de Caelo lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9</hi>
               </note> that the heavens by the revolutions of their orbs produce a moſt melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and divine harmonie, and that as they are the meaſures of naturall time, ſo they keep an harmonious time. He pawne no faith upon it, that thoſe <hi>Orbs</hi> are the <hi>great Organ to that higher quire</hi> of Archangels, Angels and glorified Saints that <hi>ſing Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs to him that ſitteth on the throne for ever and ever.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 4.13.</note> But, ſure I am, there is not more of various har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony there, then there is hereof unpleaſing diſcord: ſo that were it poſſible with <hi>Scipio</hi> in his <hi>dreame,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. Somni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Scipio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> from heaven to behold the earth (at that diſtance like a Mole-hill) and men like little Ants buſie in the eager proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their unquiet deſires, ſo to heare all the ejaculations and prayers of mortalls, we ſhould not ſee ſo much varietie of tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous motion, as we ſhould
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19937:16"/>heare of diſtaſt and paſſion. What murmurs, complaints, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinings: what clamorous fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, harſhneſſe, whining tuchineſſe ſhould we heer? How many notes of diſcontent and paſſion harſhly grate upon our eares, and a world full of <hi>ne ſic quaeſo's, not ſoes, not ſo my Lord:</hi> all unquiet, and in all and every condition and eſtate a generall diſtaſt and frowardneſſe, one praying for that which another prayes againſt, one deſiring that which another execrates, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one envying the condition of other, weary and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their own, and both and all, in their diſagreeing wiſhes, agreeing in this harſh and unpleaſing note. <hi>O ne ſic quaeſo, Domine mi, O not ſo my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will not wonder at the poore Gally-ſlave, who is forced under the rigid exaction of a cruell maſter, at each tug to wrack nature, to the height of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19937:17"/>her endevour, and with his pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſighes and drops of ſweat to wreſtle with, nay overcome the oppoſition of windes and waves, if you heare from this miſerable wretch, vented amongſt his ſighes, <hi>Ne ſic quaeſo, Domine mi, O not ſo my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You will not wonder that the poore labourer that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the price of his bread upon his forehead, and is forced to make the wheele turne with no other Oyle then his own ſweat, if you heare the ſame from him.</p>
            <p>Nor will you wonder at the poore wretch, that lyes gaſping in the Suburbs of death (whoſe gaſping 'tis hard to ſay whether it be to take in or let goe the poore remainder of his breath) you will not wonder if he, caſt downe upon the hard bed of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, in a diſcontented fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe rebound againe, like a ſtone toward the hand that caſt him, with his <hi>Ne ſic quaeſo, Domine
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19937:17"/>mi, O not ſo my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But will you wonder to heare the rich man, upon whom the world flowes, like the ſetting of the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> one way without a returne, a <hi>Moitie</hi> of whoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are both the wiſh and envy of thouſands; whoſe labour is but recreation, and the ſtudy of others but to pleaſe him; whom faire pleaſure in the varietie of all her dreſſes courteth? Will you wonder that ſuch an one, in his choice of worldly pleaſures ſhould have his <hi>ne ſic quaeſo,</hi> that ſuch a one could have any the leaſt diſtaſt? But ſo it is.</p>
            <p>Nor need we indeed to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. What can all theſe outward things comfort a man in a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing diſeaſe? This <hi>diſplicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſui,</hi> is a ſickneſſe of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Since <hi>Adam</hi> firſt eate that forbidden Apple <hi>our Teeth are ſet on edge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 11. 2</note> ſo that we diſrelliſh even <hi>Angels food, Manna.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 21.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The malignitie of our wit
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19937:18"/>can finde a fault where <hi>God</hi> never made any, and this diſlike of all <hi>Gods</hi> actions and cenſure of the whole courſe of his providence is an <hi>Epidemicall,</hi> and generall diſeaſe of man. For indeed who is there amongſt all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> that can juſtly ſay, his obedience moveth in a direct ſubordination to that firſt mover of all things? that with a ready will, he acteth the precepts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that with an humble patience, abideth the puniſhments inflicted? No, no, ſince that fall of our firſt parents, the beſt of our obedience halteth, and our patience is frowardneſſe.</p>
            <p>If <hi>God</hi> impoſe any taske to be performed, inflict any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be indured, which is diſtaſtfull to the palate of our ſickned nature, O tis impoſſible to doe the one, intollerable to ſuffer the other; with what fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe we goe about the one, and undergoe the other, and yet
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19937:18"/>how little reaſon we have ſo to doe, let us ſee in <hi>Lot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why ſhould we deny obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>Gods</hi> commands, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe our <hi>not ſo,</hi> when <hi>God</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands alwayes for our owne good?</p>
            <p>Firſt, then <hi>goe to the mountaine</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and be ſafe, thy diſobedience is a negative to thine owne ſafety.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is thy <hi>Lord;</hi> how <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ill coupled are theſe two, <hi>ne ſic,</hi> with <hi>Domine mi, not ſo,</hi> with <hi>my Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, thou art his <hi>Servant,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and is <hi>ne ſis,</hi> a <hi>fit dialect</hi> for a <hi>ſervus tuus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, thou <hi>haſt found grace in his ſight,</hi> and where is thy <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> thankfulneſſe for his favours paſt?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, he hath <hi>ſaved thy life,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> where is thy confidence then for the time to come? if thou obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt him he will ſave it ſtill: all theſe might have beene motives to <hi>Lot's</hi> obedience, and checkes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19937:19"/>to his <hi>ne ſic,</hi> to his <hi>not ſo;</hi> yet all are nothing, the authoritie of a <hi>Lord,</hi> the dutie of a <hi>Servant,</hi> the <hi>mercy</hi> of a deliverer, the <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for this grace obtained in ſaving his life.</hi> He is thy <hi>Lord,</hi> by authoritie he may command, thou his <hi>Servant,</hi> 'tis thy dutie to obey, and thou mayeſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to it: but thou art a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite to him, it will be the part of thy <hi>thankefulneſſe,</hi> nay ſuch a favourite as oweſt <hi>thy life,</hi> and therefore ſhouldeſt venture it in his ſervice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lot</hi> offended therefore againſt his owne <hi>ſafety,</hi> againſt the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of his Lord,</hi> againſt the <hi>dutie of a ſervant,</hi> againſt <hi>Gods mercie</hi> delivering, againſt the Lawes of <hi>thankefulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Lot cannot eſcape to the mountaine. Cannot!</hi> then in vaine are theſe Lawes of a <hi>Lord,</hi> of a <hi>Servant,</hi> of gratitude urged if <hi>Lot cannot obey.</hi> But let us ſee the ſtrength of his reaſon, if that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19937:19"/>will excuſe the weakneſſe of his <hi>I cannot;</hi> firſt in a generall ſurvey after in a more full examination of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot (ſayes Lot) ne fortè ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod makim capiat &amp; moriar, leſt ſome evill take me, and I die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, there is <hi>fortè malum,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance ſome evill.</p>
            <p>Secondly, But what evill? nay that he knowes not, it's but <hi>aliquod malum, ſome evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, let there be more than <hi>fortè,</hi> a certaine evill, more than <hi>aliquod,</hi> let there be <hi>malum horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, informe, ingens,</hi> a great one: what then? <hi>O nè fortè capiat, Leſt it take him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, well! be it ſo too; let there be an <hi>evill,</hi> and that <hi>evill a great one,</hi> and <hi>that great one take him,</hi> yet <hi>et moriar, Leſt it take me, and I die.</hi> What's in all this to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe either the boldnes of his <hi>not ſo,</hi> or the weakneſſe of his <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</hi> For</p>
            <p>Firſt, it's cauſuall, whether
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19937:20"/>there be, not <hi>mala,</hi> but ſo much as <hi>malum</hi> in the ſingular, <hi>any one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it's caſuall, if there be <hi>malum,</hi> what it is: for it's but <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè, aliquod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It's caſuall thirdly, <hi>ſi ſit malum aliquod, &amp; hoc aliquod grande, utrum capiat,</hi> if there be an <hi>evill,</hi> and that <hi>evill a great one,</hi> it's caſuall whether <hi>it take him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>ſi ſit malum, &amp; hoc malum grande, &amp; hoc grande capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat, utrum moriar,</hi> if there be an <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> and this <hi>evill a great one,</hi> and this great one <hi>take him,</hi> it's caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all whether it <hi>be mortall:</hi> And yet <hi>Lot cannot, will not, dare not go to the mountaine, ne forte aliquod ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, &amp;c. Leſt ſome evill take him, and he die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, as <hi>dividedly</hi> I have weighed his arguments, and have found them light, let me ſet one part of the Text againſt another, and as in a picture, you ſhall have the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of the one, to ſet of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19937:20"/>the <hi>ſight</hi> of the other.</p>
            <p>But firſt the <hi>ſubject</hi> of both parts <hi>(thy ſervant)</hi> muſt runne through both parts, and in that there's an argument, both againſt his <hi>ne ſic,</hi> and <hi>ne fortè:</hi> his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient <hi>ne,</hi> and his deſtruſting <hi>nè.</hi> For if <hi>Lot</hi> be <hi>Gods ſervant, in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitute tuâ perfecta libert as,</hi> in Gods ſervice is perfect freedome <hi>Gods ſervant</hi> that hath <hi>God's</hi> paſſe, may goe through fire and water, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Swords and Cannons, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall hurt him.</p>
            <p>Now for collating of the parts.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing in <hi>Lot's</hi> way is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>fortè: ne fortè,</hi> leſt perhaps, leſt perchance. For that, againſt <hi>ne fortè</hi> I'le ſet <hi>conſpectus tuus: Ecce invenit ſervus tuus gratiam in conſpectu tuo;</hi> the <hi>eye of God's</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence againſt <hi>blinde obance,</hi> and then ſhall not <hi>Gods eye</hi> ſee better to guard thee, then <hi>blinde fortune</hi> to hit thee?</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſtop is <hi>aliquod malum,</hi> and in that I'le grant the moſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19937:21"/>that it is <hi>magnum or ingens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum:</hi> and then, <hi>magnitudini ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li hujus or miſeriae,</hi> I will ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it <hi>magnificaſti magnitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem miſericordiae,</hi> to the <hi>greatneſſe</hi> of this <hi>evill</hi> or miſery, the <hi>greatnes of Gods mercy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.9.</note> And let that which is <hi>above all his works,</hi> anſwer the feare of the greateſt <hi>evill</hi> that can betide him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, againſt <hi>capiat,</hi> I'le ſet <hi>inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gratiam,</hi> he's accepted of God; let <hi>acceptus</hi> then ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goinſt <hi>captus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly againſt <hi>moriar</hi> I'le ſet <hi>ſervando vitam,</hi> againſt <hi>lest I die,</hi> I'le ſet <hi>in ſaving my life.</hi> And now collecting all, what reaſon had <hi>Lot</hi> to treſpaſſe againſt the <hi>authority of his Lord,</hi> againſt the <hi>duty of a ſervant,</hi> againſt the <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of his deliverer? Why for fear of a <hi>fortè,</hi> who was in <hi>conſpecta Dei,</hi> in Gods ſight? Why for fear of any <hi>evill,</hi> who had <hi>found grace in the ſight of God?</hi> Why of the <hi>greateſt evill,</hi> who had taſted <hi>Gods
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19937:21"/>mercy magnified</hi> towards him? Why for fear any <hi>evill ſhould take him,</hi> who was <hi>accepted of God?</hi> Why for feare of looſing <hi>his life,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> had ſo graciouſly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</p>
            <p>It is diſputed by <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> in his firſt book of his <hi>Noctes At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A. Gellius.</hi> lib. 1. noct. artic.</note> whether a <hi>ſervant</hi> receiving ſuch or ſuch injunctions from his <hi>Lord,</hi> may upon aſſurance of his maſters greater profit, either leave undone his maſters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or vary from it in any point or circumſtance of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Or whether there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in a ſervant ſuch an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which the <hi>Schools</hi> call <hi>cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, infinitum, and irrationalem;</hi> ſo that he ought to obſerve pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually the command of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, whether any unexpected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident threaten loſſe and diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to accrew by doing that which was commanded, and an aſſured profit by doing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. 'Tis neither proper to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19937:22"/>this place nor my purpoſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute this queſtion, only give me leave to relate a Story by him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, with which he ſeems to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Craſſus Mutianus,</hi> a man that by <hi>Sempronius Aſellio,</hi> &amp; other hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians is reported to have bin hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in the joynt fruition of five of the greateſt and chiefeſt of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane bleſſings, That he was the richeſt of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the moſt eloquent, the moſt skilfull in the Lawes, and laſtly, that he was High-Prieſt.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Craſſus</hi> obtaining the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and there beſieging a City called <hi>Leuca,</hi> ſends to the chief Enginier of the <hi>Molealenſes,</hi> (a People then in confederacy with the <hi>Romanes</hi>) to ſend him of two maſts which he had ſeene in their City, the ſtronger and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, of which he might make a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ramme to batter the wals of the beſieged City. The Enginier being a skilfull man, and ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19937:22"/>with himſelf the uſe of the maſt, ſends him, not according to the direction, the bigger, but that which he knew both eaſier for carriage, and more fit for that uſe, which was the leſſe. <hi>Craſſus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds him to becal'd for, inquires why he ſent not that which was commanded, &amp; deſpiſing all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he could alleadge, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to be ſtripped &amp; ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with rods. Before you brand <hi>Craſſus</hi> with the name of tyrant, beſides that you heare the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his wiſedome, heare a ſecond in his reaſon. He thought <hi>(ſaith mine author)</hi> all authority would be cheap and vile, <hi>ſi quis ad id quod facere juſſus eſt, non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequio debibito, ſed conſilio non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderato reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deat,</hi> if a ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t might excuſe the duty of his obedience to which he is called by the ſauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his own advice to which he was not called; and that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience would be too much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiz'd, if a ſervant might have
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19937:23"/>the liberty to make his owne counſell the <hi>Oracle,</hi> at which his obedience would conſult, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould do or not do what his Lord commands.</p>
            <p>If the authority of mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands be ſo great and abſolute, that it exacts obedience peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and that obedience either neglected or altered, though up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the faireſt pretences of the commander's profit, honour &amp;c. deſerve ſo ſevere a puniſhment, with <hi>how many ſtripes ſhalt thou be beaten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.47</note> 
               <hi>thou evill ſervant,</hi> that doſt diſobey, not man, but <hi>God,</hi> and that not for any reaſon on his behalfe (as that poor wretch that was ſcourged for <hi>Craſſus</hi> his) but for thine owne private reſpects, honour, profit, pleaſure, dareſt, though a ſervant, a creature, make thine own ends a ſufficient reaſon to infringe the lawes of the <hi>Lord,</hi> thy Creator, of thy <hi>God</hi> that cannot be deceived, of <hi>God</hi> that needs not any advice, or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19937:23"/>the correction of ſecond thoughts? <hi>For he neither deceiveth nor can be deceived,</hi> of <hi>God</hi> that hath ſo abſolute a power, by ſo many rights over ſoul and body, whoſe authority and direction are above queſtioning either the power of the one, or the wiſdome of the other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Centurion ſaith to one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 8 9.</note> 
               <hi>go, and be goeth, to another, come, and he cometh, to his ſervant, do this, and he doth it.</hi> Shall <hi>God</hi> that is not as he, <hi>under authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> but <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all,</hi> and from whom all other is derived, have leſſe power over us? Let him ſay go, or come, or do this or that, he can heare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>ne ſic, not ſo my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was argument enough in the Schoole of <hi>Pythagoras <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ipſe dixit, Pythagoras ſaid ſo,</hi> to infer the truth of any <hi>paradox,</hi> and the faith of the Schooles is now a daies taught that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (if I ſay not ſlavery) that in <hi>Philoſophy, Ariſtotle</hi> is like an <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19937:24"/>Pope,</hi> whoſe text is avouched with the authoritie of <hi>Canonicall Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſhall <hi>riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the men of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth 12.41, 42.</note> yea and <hi>ſhall condemne them too,</hi> for they beleeve the ſayings of <hi>Pythagor as</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.</note> and <hi>behold a greater then both is here,</hi> that great <hi>Rabbi,</hi> that is <hi>the way the truth and the life,</hi> yet let him ſpeak and we beleeve not his word, command and we obey not his law, but queſtion both the truth of the one and deny the anthority of the other, with <hi>not ſo my Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre of <hi>Lots</hi> Negative requeſt, with the ſummary view, and ballancing his reaſons, it now remaines that I proceed to a more full and particular ſurvey of the reaſons which <hi>Lot</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to juſtifie this diſlike of Gods Councell, and maintaine his owne opinion. And the firſt is from the <hi>difficultie of the taske.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19937:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The way of the ſloathfull man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is upon thornes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 15.19.</note> Mans unwillingneſſe creates a difficultie in the moſt eaſie enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and his feare a danger in the moſt ſecure way. <hi>I cannot,</hi> is many times and in many men nothing elſebut <hi>I will not,</hi> or <hi>I have no minde</hi> to this or that, and ſo me thinkes it ſeemes to ſound here, rather like a voyce procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the reluctancie of an unſubdued will, then the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of a fainting ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a Lyon in the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 26.13.</note> ſaith <hi>the ſloathfull man;</hi> there are a thouſand dangers, ſaith the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing minde. Unwillingneſſe creates monſters, and ſets them up in her owne way, to which (like <hi>Nabuchadnezzer to the Image himſelfe had made:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.1.</note> it fals downe in feare, as he in reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Thus her owne fancies fright her, and with an unhappy skilfulneſſe, where ſhe findes no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19937:25"/>feares, her owne feares makes them.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, tis neer a miracle to obſerve, how much a ready and forward willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can effect. Danger and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie are not lets, but ſpurres to her undaunted reſolution, and ſo farre from amateing her, that they rather animate her; like a bullet that by graſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine mounts, it takes a new and freſh courage at each obſtacle, and in an heroicall diſdaine of the leaſt affront, revenges in the ſecond onſet the diſgrace of the firſt repulſe.</p>
            <p>Had <hi>Lot</hi> then brought a minde as willing to be commanded, as the command was in it ſelfe eaſie to be obeyed, there had been no exceptions, no demurs between <hi>Gods</hi> command and his executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no pretences of fained feares, and divinations of I know not what <hi>evils</hi> might <hi>take him:</hi> but rather with a ready willingneſſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19937:25"/>and induſtrious alacritie, he ſhould have ſhewed his <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>Gods</hi> authoritie commanding, his <hi>faith</hi> to <hi>Gods</hi> Wiſedome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting, and how ever, his <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi> to <hi>Gods mercie</hi> delivering: he ſhould then have ſaid as the <hi>ſervants in Naaman</hi> to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 5.13. <hi>If the Lord had bid thee doe ſome great thing,<note place="margin">2 King. 5.13.</note> wouldſt thou not havè done it, how much rather when he ſath eſcape to the mountaines and he ſafe?</hi> or he would have taken up the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Shimei to Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 2.38.</note> 2.38. <hi>The ſaying is very good, as my Lord hath ſaid, ſo will thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant doe:</hi> he would have anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his <hi>feares</hi> with his <hi>faith,</hi> and ſilenced his <hi>reaſon</hi> with his <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> he would have done any thing but diſobeyed, ſuffered any thing, or any <hi>evill,</hi> rather then have requited ſo gracious a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with ſo diſtaſtfull a reply, as <hi>not ſo my Lord, for I cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us ſee what exceptions
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19937:26"/>his ſluggiſh feare can make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Gods</hi> injunction. <hi>Eſcape to the mountaine.</hi> Why <hi>cannot Lot? I cannot eſcape to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine leaſt ſome evill take me and I dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> beſtowes an invalueable favour, which his thankfulneſſe ſhould have heard with all joy, and executed with all readineſſe. But behold delayes to <hi>Gods</hi> haſt, exceptions to <hi>his</hi> Counſell, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of <hi>his</hi> protection, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a flat deniall to <hi>his</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, a frowardneſſe, and repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning teachineſſe, which would rather runne back in to the flame and periſh in <hi>Sodom,</hi> then be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in <hi>the mountaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſcape to the mountaine!</hi> ſaith froward <hi>Lot;</hi> theirs a command hath much kindneſſe in it, that drives me into more hazzards then it ſhuunes, and for one dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger eſcaped thruſts me on an hundred? There's a journey in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: to be performed by an
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19937:26"/>aged Father, with a couple of young and tender Virgins, and to be performed by ſuch, and by ſuch in haſte, and in haſte by them that are overcharged with an heavy burden of ſorrow, for loſſe of kindred, goods, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and all; already even halfe fainting with this ſodaine vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and expectation of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of wonders: a journey of that length as muſt needs make ſome or all of us faint out right in the way, and ſo be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by the fire behinde, or any other inconvenience which our weakneſſe may give or others take to deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>But ſure the tediouſneſſe of this long way, will be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced in the end and the place we goe to make amends, for the difficultie of the way through which we goe. Alas no: when with much wearineſſe we have overcome the tediouſneſſe of the way, whether come we? From
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19937:27"/>
               <hi>a Citie</hi> to <hi>a Mountaine,</hi> from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ſome ſweets of a pleaſant valley to the diſconſolate lone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of a vaſt wilderneſſe: from a place ſurfeited with the delights of nature, to a deſert that cannot ſupply her very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities: from pleaſant ſocietie, to a melancholike ſolitarineſſe, where life is a tediouſneſſe, and nothing elſe but a perpetuated act of a living death. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Lord,</hi> if (as thou pretendeſt) thou doſt truely purpoſe, and wilt magnifie that mercie which thou haſt ſhewed to me hitherto: Then, <hi>O not ſo my Lord, for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape to the mountaine, leaſt ſome evill take me and I dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus hath <hi>Lot</hi> found <hi>Gods</hi> Counſell guiltie of hazzard and inconvenience by a jury of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and produced many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to prove it as full of hazzard as he of jealoufies, and yet all indeed, but the ſurmiſes of his feare and pretences of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing minde.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19937:27"/>
            <p>So doth mans nature ever ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill againſt Gods commands, they are like this journey to <hi>Lot,</hi> up hill, hard and dangerous, the precepts he impoſeth are impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be done,<note place="margin">Hujus legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus omnia delicta ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite plecte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur: ob quam cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam Dema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des dicere ſolebat, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conem non atramento ſed ſanguine leges Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſse. <hi>Vid. A. Gelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. lib. 11. cap 18.</hi>
               </note> the croſſes he inflicteth impoſſible to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, his Commandements are like the Lawes of <hi>Draco</hi> written in bloud, ſuch as are to <hi>deny our ſelves; goe out from the world: plucke out our right eye: cut of our right hand, and caſt them from us: turne our left cheeke to him that ſmites on the right: love our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: crucifie our affections,</hi> ſtarve our appetites in a voluntary ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemiouſneſſe. <hi>Paradoxes,</hi> (ſaith nature) full of contrarietie to the principles that were borne with us,<note place="margin">Mar. 8.34.</note> full of harſhneſſe to our appetites,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> abſurditie to our reaſon,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.29.30.39.44.</note> impoſſible to our ſtrength. <hi>Hard ſayings who can heare them, who c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n beare them?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.44.</note> And yet ſaith our Saviour.<note place="margin">Ioh 6 60.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.30.<note place="margin">Marth 11.30.</note> 
               <hi>My yoake is eaſie and my
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19937:28"/>burden is light:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.24.35.47 77.174.</note> and <hi>David, thy Teſtimonies are my delight:</hi> and the Apoſtles after their ſtripes <hi>went away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.41.</note> 
               <hi>rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer for the name of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How then? the difficultie lyes in the perverſeneſſe of <hi>mans will,</hi> not in the <hi>bardneſſe of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</hi> As therefore the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4 3.</note> 
               <hi>if our Goſpel be beds, 'tis hid to them that periſh;</hi> ſo ſay I, if <hi>Gods</hi> commands be abſurd, 'tis ſo <hi>to them onely who have not their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcerne good and evill:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> and if it be harſh, it is to them onely <hi>that ſavour not the things of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 16.23.</note> if it be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.5.</note> tis onely to him <hi>that truſteth in the arme of fleſh and maketh not God his ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conquer then thy <hi>Will,</hi> and in that one conqueſt thou over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comeſt all other difficulties: get but that maſtery of that, and then the wayes of <hi>God</hi> ſhall be like the motion of <hi>Nature,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19937:28"/>ſmooth, and without rubor let, accompanied with earneſtneſſe in the onſet, delight in the midſt and ſucceſſe in the end. Let <hi>God</hi> command what he will, thy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſhall anſwer,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeake Lord for thy ſervant heareth: as my Lord hath ſaid, ſo will thy ſervant doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King 2.38.</note> and then ſhall it appeare as ſarre from truth, as thy thought, to anſwer as <hi>Lot, not ſo my Lord for I cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But tis now more then time to weigh his reaſon, and ſee what <hi>ſtrength</hi> in that, can excuſe his <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> in his <hi>I cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leaſt ſome evill take me, and I dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is this all <hi>Lot</hi> can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, a ſurmiſe, a nothing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove <hi>Gods</hi> Conncell, and prove his owne <hi>I cannot?</hi> Alas, what canſt thou weake man, if thou canſt not this? What will not poſe the beſt of thy ſtrength, if a meere ſurmiſe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>à fortè,</hi> if an
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19937:29"/>
               <hi>aliquid,</hi> if a <hi>leſt</hi> and <hi>ſome evill</hi> can doe it?</p>
            <p>O the weakneſſe of diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man! What are we, while we hold not faſt on the Rocke <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the beſt of us a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> a <hi>Gedeon,</hi> a <hi>Lot?</hi> Behold a champion one of the <hi>Lords wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies;</hi> yet ſee his ſtrength, (his weakneſſe I ſhould ſay) ſee what can trouble him. Heres no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie of evill, nor needs there any to perplexe him: a feare, a thought, a very ſhaddow will ſerve to melt his ſubſtance into the cold ſwet of feare: a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of his owne, <hi>Ne fortè malum, leaſt perhaps evill,</hi> and <hi>ne fortè aliquod, leaſt ſome evill;</hi> I know not what <hi>evill,</hi> 'tis <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate,</hi> and <hi>ne fortè ſi aliquod malum ſit (capiat, leaſt ſome evill take me,</hi> and <hi>ne fortè) ſi aliquod malum ſit, &amp; capiat nè moriar,</hi> leaſt if it <hi>take him it be mortall, leaſt ſome evill take we and I dye.</hi> It's <hi>caſuall</hi> whether there be an
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19937:29"/>
               <hi>evill;</hi> tis <hi>caſuall</hi> if there be, what <hi>it</hi> is; it is <hi>caſuall</hi> if it be, and be great, whether it <hi>take him;</hi> laſtly it is <hi>caſuall</hi> if it <hi>be one,</hi> and that one a <hi>great one,</hi> and it <hi>take him,</hi> whether <hi>he dye,</hi> and yet <hi>righteous Lot cannot,</hi> dare not, will not <hi>goe the mountaine, ne fortè aliquod malum capiat &amp; moriar, leaſt ſome evill take me and I dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What needs the bloudy ſword of the ſlaying Angel, as againſt the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 19.35.</note> the <hi>fighting of the Starres in their courſes, as againſt Siſera,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 5.20.</note> the warring of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Gen. 19 24.</note> as <hi>falling of fire from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 5.12.</note> as <hi>on Sodom,</hi> infection of the <hi>ayre</hi> as againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 6.11 13.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowing of <hi>Water</hi> as on the old world,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.20, 21.</note> gaping of the <hi>Earth</hi> as on <hi>Corab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb 16 31, 32.</note> 
               <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram?</hi> What need the <hi>ſwarmes of flyes, bands of locuſts, frogs, lice</hi> orot her his creatures, which ſtand ready to be the agents and miniſters of his vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19937:30"/>ſinfull man, when <hi>God</hi> can make <hi>man himſelf</hi> his owne puniſher; <hi>his owne</hi> feares, his owne imaginary feares, his own torment and executioner, drive him with himſelf, from himſelf, even to ſuch an extaſie of feare, as ſhall make him (to cure them) to compound with the <hi>King of feares death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note> and make <hi>a covenant with hell,</hi> that he may ſhunne the preſent horrour of <hi>hell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, to ſhew as well the weakneſſe of <hi>Lots</hi> argument, as of his <hi>I cannot:</hi> ſuppoſe for thy <hi>fortè,</hi> a <hi>reall evill,</hi> for this <hi>aliquod, one certaine,</hi> and of certaine dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, yet might he have ſtood aſſured in the <hi>capiat and monia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that it ſhould neither <hi>take him, nor he dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what? doth thy <hi>fortè</hi> deifie a blinde chance, and put out the <hi>eye of Gods providence?</hi> or hath that providence (which thou muſt needs confeſſe in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>) left thee at the gates of it,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19937:30"/>and will accompany thee no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? or was thy ſafety from the throngs of the <hi>Citie,</hi> that thou art afraide to be with God alone in the mountaine? or doſt thou thinke him, as they did after,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>a God of vallies and not of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine?</hi> or if thou thinke none of theſe, why doſt thou thinke there can be any danger in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Gods</hi> Counſell or command? Doſt thou thinke <hi>He</hi> doth taske thy obedience with a command that hath any danger, <hi>who</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth command thy obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that thou mayſt eſcape a danger? If thou thinkeſt <hi>Gods</hi> purpoſe be not to deliver, why wilt thou leave <hi>Sodom,</hi> why wilt thou obey in <hi>that?</hi> If thou thinkeſt <hi>Gods</hi> purpoſe to be to deliver thee, why doſt thou not obey in <hi>this?</hi> Why not to <hi>the mountaine,</hi> doſt thou thinke the <hi>neerer heaven</hi> thou goeſt, thou goeſt the <hi>further from</hi> him that is the <hi>God of heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19937:31"/>
            <p>Well mighteſt thou have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered thy feares, as the <hi>Wife of Manoah</hi> did her husbands. <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.23. <hi>If the Lord</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>were pleaſed to kill us, he would not have accepted a burnt offering at our hands, neither would he have ſhewed us all theſe things.</hi> So might <hi>Lot</hi> have argued. Did the <hi>Lord</hi> deliver me from ſo great a danger as the flames of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and will he betray me to my petty feares in the Wilderneſſe, and <hi>He</hi> with whom Angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed not to lodge, will they not <hi>pitch their Tents about my Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note> to guard me? and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if <hi>God</hi> was pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale his counſell to me of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying <hi>Sodom,</hi> would he not as well have told me of any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, if any were? is not that power, which can ſo miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly puniſh the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> great enough to preſerve me, if he be willing, and that he is willing, this deliverance from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19937:31"/>this common judgement aſſures me of more then common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour? <hi>Non poteſt tot miraculorum filius perire,</hi> he for whom ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miracles were done its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible he ſhould miſcarry.</p>
            <p>I will therefore obey readily (might <hi>Lot</hi> ſay) ſince God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands lovingly, I will goe, ſince <hi>God</hi> ſends me, and though my reaſon diſpute againſt it, and my feares preſent me with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand hazzards, Ile neglect all: I have a commiſſion, <hi>Gods</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand will carry me through an boaſt of oppoſing dangers.</p>
            <p>For indeed, what is it that I can feare? is it <hi>ſolitarineſſe?</hi> He is never alone whom <hi>God accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies.</hi> Is it <hi>melancholy?</hi> the <hi>light of Gods countenance ſhall ſhine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me.</hi> Is it <hi>theeves?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.6.</note> amongſt a throng of men violently bent to deſtroy me, God delivered me, by blinding them, and cannot he much more hide me from a few wandring robbers? Or is it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19937:32"/>
               <hi>want? He feedeth the young ravens when they call upon him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 147.9.</note> nay he can make <hi>the young ravens feed his ſervant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 17.4.6.</note> Or is it laſt of all, <hi>wilde beaſts?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.33.</note> he can <hi>ſtop the Lyons mouthes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>and the wilde beasts ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all his holy mountaine.</hi> What is it that thou canſt feare? is it any of theſe, or all of theſe or more then all? Yet,<note place="margin">Rom. 8 31.</note> 
               <hi>if God be with thee who can be againſt thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet all <hi>Gods</hi> former favours <hi>reall</hi> and <hi>many,</hi> cannot winne the conqueſt of theſe few, and thoſe onely ſuppoſed feares: but he unthankfully forgets the one, and ſluggiſhly yields to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> was pleaſed to make <hi>Lot</hi> his <hi>boaſt,</hi> but now he makes his <hi>gueſt a ſtranger:</hi> his ſafety in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> coſt <hi>God</hi> a miracle, the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of many: yet <hi>Lot,</hi> more blind then they, thinkes him ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent who is every where preſent, <hi>in whom he lives,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>moves, and hath
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19937:32"/>his being,</hi> gropes with more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie then the <hi>Sodomites for Lots doore;</hi> for him that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, without, above, beneath, fills all places, and is excluded from no place, for him that goes where he will he cannot miſſe. Yet <hi>Lot</hi> ſluggiſhly yeelds to his owne feares, and the miracle that God had ſhewed in <hi>blinding the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> and <hi>carrying him without the Citie,</hi> cannot winne the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of his diſtruſt, but he feares to follow Gods directions, <hi>leaſt ſome evill take him, and he dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am divided in my wonder at <hi>Gods patience, and mans diſtruſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take here then firſt a meaſure of that which is indeed <hi>immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable, the Patience and long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Almightie God,</hi> whom though we <hi>daily,</hi> hourely, nay each minute <hi>provoke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.12.</note> and anſwer every act of his goodneſſe, with ſome fact of our unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet ſtill he continues his mercies, and even while we are
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19937:33"/>finning againſt him, even then, is he doing good to us.</p>
            <p>What mercy not more then morall and mortall ſo ill requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what <hi>patience</hi> leſſe then <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite</hi> ſo often abuſed, would not turne to revenging fury, breake forth into wrath and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation?</p>
            <p>Excuſe the homelineſſe of a <hi>fable,</hi> and let the goodneſſe of the morall win your pardon of the tale it ſelf. Tis thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A mortall</hi> being in heaven, from whence he might behold the earth, as a little Mole-hill, and men, like Ants, buſie in the eager purſuit of their unquiet deſires; amongſt other things he ſees a thief picking the purſe of one that had lately before ſaved his life. Our <hi>mortall</hi> being paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately angry at ſo foule ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and unable by reaſon of the diſtance to call to them, grew ſo inraged that he caught up <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piters tripos,</hi> and threw it at the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19937:33"/>malefactor. <hi>Iupiter</hi> enquires for the author and cauſe of his throwing, and finding it, <hi>exeant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>èeoelo affectus mortales, qui dum, &amp;c.</hi> Away with mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall affections out of heaven, and from the government of the world,<note place="margin">Si quoties peccant homines ſua, &amp;c.</note> which would quickly ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leave no ſtooles in heaven or no men on earth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>morall</hi> ſhewes us the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> that it would be woe unto the world, if <hi>God</hi> were, as man touched with humane paſſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, take notice here of <hi>mans diſtrust,</hi> God had graciouſly wreſtled with <hi>Lots</hi> dulneſſe, and when he would have by his ſloathfulneſſe and delayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed himſelfe, was pleaſed, (rather then he would let <hi>Lot</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy himſelfe) to uſe a loving violence, by force <hi>to carry him and ſet him without the Citie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.16</note> Yet now, him that <hi>God</hi> would ſave, when he neglected himſelfe, he
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19937:34"/>feares that <hi>God</hi> would neglect him, when he would ſave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Never had man more cauſe of confidence. So many favours might have excuſed if not patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized an over bold preſumption, and ſet him ſo farre from diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and feare of danger, that he might with farre more reaſon have run into a neglective care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſeneſſe of himſelfe and danger. He might have found ſeeming reaſons, and a ſhew of argument for ſuch a fault, but there is not in all <hi>the topickes of invention</hi> any argument or colour to hide ſo foule a diſtruſt.</p>
            <p>What obſtinacy and baſeneſſe is in the diſtruſtfulneſſe of man? The arguments of <hi>Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> are beyond our numbering multiplied even with the minutes of our lives, and yet are our feares more frequent then our dangers. Let <hi>God</hi> deliver us from the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt evils, we dare not truſt <hi>him</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:19937:34"/>in the leaſt: deliver us from a thouſand, yet we dare not truſt <hi>him</hi> in one. All <hi>his</hi> mercies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to us, in beſtowing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall favours upon us, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting imminent dangers, in delivering us out of many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions that have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed us, all theſe cannot merit our truſt in <hi>him,</hi> or arme us with undaunted confidence againſt an appearance of danger; but as if there were no <hi>God,</hi> or as if that <hi>God ſlumbered and ſlept,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 121.4.</note> and intermedled not in the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world (as the Stoicks fondly dreamed) we ſhrinke and tremble at ſight of every danger, and to ſecure our ſelves thinke it a ſurer way to run to unlawfull ſhifts, then relye on the aſſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Gods providence.</hi> And as if <hi>Gods hand were too ſhort</hi> to reach from Heaven; we thinke it a farre ſafer way to catch hold of that which is next us, even any poore, unlawfull, and therefore
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19937:35"/>helpes ſhift which our owne rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhewes unto us. So wanting that <hi>eye of faith (which is the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of things not ſeene)</hi> and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely with the <hi>eye of ſence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> we judge that <hi>God</hi> nor ſees nor regards, becauſe we ſee not <hi>him.</hi> Each new danger awakes a new diſtruſt.</p>
            <p>What teſtimonies had God given to the captive <hi>Jewes of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> of an eſpeciall love to them, that for their ſakes had ſhewed the <hi>ſtrength of his mighty</hi> arme,<note place="margin">Exod. 13.14.16.</note> in ſo many <hi>unheard of wonders?</hi> Is it in the belief of man that any danger could beget their diſtruſt? Yet ſee,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.29.</note> they are no ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, by the death of ſo many ſoules as <hi>that night of horrour</hi> cauſed (that might indeed be red <hi>for them</hi> and bluſh at their ſo fowle, ſo monſtrous diſtruſt) but <hi>they</hi> on the firſt occaſion are ready to undervalue their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and wiſh rather to have <hi>ſerved the Egyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 14.10.11.12.</note> then to <hi>dye</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:19937:35"/>(as they feared) <hi>in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A deliverance may yeild us comfort for the preſent, but as if of a <hi>tranſeunt nature</hi> it ends there, and ſeldome doe we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it to arme us in the future, ſo relying on tranſitory and vaine helpes, every aſſault of danger looſes the joynts and ſhakes the ſtrongeſt of our weak built reſolutions.</p>
            <p>If <hi>God</hi> ſhould ſay to us in our miſery as he did unto the <hi>two blind men,</hi> Matt. 9.29. <hi>According to your faith be it unto you;</hi> it would be ill with us, each affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction would overcome us, and the ſhrinking of our faith ſoone call on us miſery enough to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme us: our owne deſpaire would open us a gulfe, a grave wherein we ſhould bury toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, both our ſelves and hopes,<note place="margin">Matth. 27.60.60.</note> upon which (like that <hi>great ſtone</hi> rowled upon <hi>Chriſts Sepulcher</hi>) our miſeries ſhould lye with ſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19937:36"/>great weight, as would cruſh, and at laſt ſhrinke us into the loweſt pit of hell.</p>
            <p>If <hi>God</hi> ſhould not finde a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter motive in his owne <hi>infinite goodneſſe,</hi> a better cauſe in his <hi>own Sonne</hi> to deliver us when we are oppreſſed, alaſſe what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, what miſery ſo poore, that is not too ſtrong for the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man? What could our knowledge foreſee? What could our wiſedome prevent, of thoſe evils we did foreſee? What could our vaine and tranſitory helpes overcome? Nay the Eye of our knowledge being diſturbed by our feare, would preſent evils with more horrour: nay ſhould not our knowledge hurt, not help us, whiles it lookes through the falſe perſpectives of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and feare, it ſo making evils greater or leſſe then indeed they are? Yea and ſhould not our wiſedome rather hurt then helpe us, while relying on the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19937:36"/>opinion of it own abilities, it rather makes us ſecure, when it could not make us ſafe? Yea and ſhould not the beſt meanes our owne wiſedome could ſupply us with, rather hurt then helpe us, when they ſhould prove one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly like <hi>broken reeds to which when we ſhould leane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 36 6</note> 
               <hi>they breake, and ſo runne into our hands?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peſſimus in dubiis augur timor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Statius, lib. <hi>1.</hi> Thebaid.</note> —Feare is the worſt Counſellor. Yet theſe tranſitory helpes, are the forts of our greateſt ſtrength, and they to which we owe both the moſt of our truſt and thanks. We deifie nature, and relye on ſelfe-unable meanes, as if a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed captive ſhould reverence the ſword and not the man that uſed it to his reſcue. Alas theſe things we truſt to, they are but <hi>agent</hi> of the <hi>firſt and prime cauſe,</hi> things which in themſelves carry an equall indifference to be as well the Miniſters of <hi>his</hi> venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as mercy. <hi>Heat,</hi> the greateſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19937:37"/>comfort of ſublunary things, ſo that it is called the <hi>Father of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> yet how often hath that father (like <hi>Saturne</hi>) eaten his owne children? <hi>Moysture, the mother of generation,</hi> yet often hath her wombe proved a tombe, and ſwallowed up her owne iſſue?</p>
            <p>There is nothing in the world proved either by more frequent or more demonſtration then <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> yet nothing in our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe more queſtioned. Who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves <hi>God</hi> further then he ſees him? Where is the <hi>faith</hi> of thoſe <hi>ancient worthies that beleeved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, againſt hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb 11.</note> againſt the <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.18.</note> and beyond the poſſibility of nature, when na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſons might call their <hi>faith</hi> abſurd, fooliſh, impoſſible? <hi>If God come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be finde faith upon the earth?</hi> ſhall he not finde it is vaniſhed into its <hi>object,</hi> and become <hi>a thing not ſeene?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> Or if we have any faith, 'tis but all
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19937:37"/>ſenſitive, and muſt take infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from our eye, our eare, our ſenſes.<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.48.</note> 
               <hi>Give the Jewes a ſigne</hi> and then perhaps <hi>they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.25.27.28.</note> Give <hi>Thomas</hi> an ocular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, <hi>Let him ſee the print of the Nailes in our Saviours hands, let him thruſt his fingers into his ſide,</hi> and then he will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>my Lord and my God.</hi> Give me ſome ground for my faith to walke on, otherwiſe I muſt needs be at the brink of deſpaire. I cannot like <hi>Peter walke upon the water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 14.29.30.</note> or if I doe, the riſing of a wave ſhall daſh my confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence into deſpaire, and as if every hollow of the waves were to become my grave, my faith and I, muſt both ſinke, and I <hi>cry</hi> out with <hi>him</hi> in deſpaire, <hi>Lord ſave me I periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But O <hi>Lord,</hi> doe not thou make good our feares to us: O be not in ſo remote a diſtance as our diffidence would ſet <hi>thee,</hi> nor yet as a judgement of our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19937:38"/>fears withdraw <hi>thy</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting favours.</p>
            <p>What uſe ſhall I make of that hath beene ſaid, but even that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, I will go unto the mountaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 121.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>from whence my help co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth:</hi> Learne to looke with the <hi>eye of faith,</hi> more than reaſon or ſenſe, and then ſhall we ſee a guard of <hi>innumerable Angels</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circling us, <hi>pitching their Tents a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bernacles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 6.17 Pſal. 34.7.</note> and let the miſeries of wanting <hi>it</hi> increaſe our deſire to get <hi>it,</hi> one <hi>graine</hi> of which, even no bigger than a <hi>graine of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 17.20.</note> if we were owners of, we might <hi>remove a mountaine,</hi> but wanting <hi>faith,</hi> a danger that is but as a <hi>graine of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi> is able to move us.</p>
            <p>But <hi>be that truſteth in the Lord ſhall be as Mount Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 125.1.</note> 
               <hi>that ſhall never be moved, but ſtandeth faſt for ever:</hi> No evill ſhall come neere him or hurt him,<note place="margin">Pſa 91.7, &amp;c.</note> and after a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous victory of all miſeries here,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.19</note>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.10.</note> he ſhall be crowned with glory
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19937:38"/>and eternity hereafter.</p>
            <p>Let us not then in a good cauſe be ever deterred, by the vaine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frights of feare or danger. The goodneſſe of the cauſe ought to animate us, in the evilneſſe and hardneſſe of the way to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh it. If God be the author, the devill cannot be the hinderer. Honeſty and goodneſſe ſhoot in ſtright lines at the laſt and <hi>beſt end Gods glory,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> will as certainly proſper <hi>the meanes</hi> as he doth propoſe the <hi>end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verum &amp; bonum convertuntur</hi> (ſay the <hi>Schooles</hi>) <hi>Truth and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are reciprocates,</hi> there is no goodneſſe without truth, no truth without goodneſſe. <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na eſt veritas &amp; vincet,</hi> great is truth, and ſhall prevaile, ſo all goodneſſe in the ſtrength of truth ſhall at laſt overcome. <hi>The winds may blow, the raine fall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 7.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>the floods beat upon thee, but thou ſhalt not fall, for thou art grounded upon a rocke.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:19937:39"/>
            <p>Haſt thou begun then a noble, a glorious action, which redounds to <hi>Gods</hi> glory, the Churches and Common-weal's good, <hi>Incapiſti benè, quis impedivit? Thou baſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>who hath hindred thee</hi> that thou continueſt not? If the action was evill, why did you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it? if the action was good, why do you not hold on? What if ſlanderers back-bite you and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you? What if authority frowne, what if envy maligne? what if the multitude <hi>rage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>and the people imagine a vaine thing?</hi> thou haſt <hi>Gods commiſſion;</hi> ſay not then I cannot, 'tis but <hi>nè fortè ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum capiat &amp; moriar,</hi> but a <hi>leſt ſome evill take me, and I dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thine owne cowardize, thine owne weakneſſe may conquer thee,<note place="margin">Pſal 2, 3.</note> but all theſe, though <hi>they take counſell together, ſhall not</hi> be able to withſtand thee. If <hi>God</hi> ſet thee on worke, he'le beare thee through, maugre the oppoſing fury of the devill and all his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19937:39"/>
               <hi>Go on then in the ſtrength of the Lord,</hi> and be victorious.<note place="margin">Pſa. 71.16.</note> I tell thee, if for the <hi>fortè,</hi> there be <hi>an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill reall,</hi> that threat thee: <hi>Sica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat</hi> if it take thee, <hi>ſi moriare,</hi> if thou die,<note place="margin">Rom. 14 8.</note> yet know whether thou live or die,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37</note> 
               <hi>thou art more than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer.</hi> It's better fall in a good cauſe than proſper in an evill one. Onely let not thy feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray Gods cauſe to miſcarriage. If death it ſelfe be threatned to thee, die. Canſt thou ever have a better end, than to die for that end for which thou and all things were made, <hi>Gods glory?</hi> which grant <hi>(O Lord)</hi> that we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe unto our ſelves, in all our thoughts, words and works, that glorifying <hi>thee</hi> in this life, we may receive eternall glory and felicity from and with <hi>thee,</hi> in the life to come, and that not for any merits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>four own, but for his ſake who hath dearly bought us, to <hi>whom</hi> with the father, and the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit,</hi> be aſcribed all honour,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19937:40"/>praiſe, and glory, now and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GENES. 19. VERS. 20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold now this City is neere to flee unto, and it is a little one. O let me eſcape thither (is it not a little one?) and my ſoule ſhall live.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a property of <hi>Divinity</hi> not to erre. Perfection is a White, at which all of us ought to aime, none may hope to hit. The beſt men have their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and imperfections, <hi>Optimus ille eſt qui minimis urgetur,</hi> he's the beſt man that hath leaſt, he's <hi>no man</hi> that hath no faults. Let <hi>him</hi> be excepted, <hi>that</hi> was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, <hi>him</hi> that being man was more then man too, CHRIST JESUS, <hi>God and man, in whom there was no fault, neither was guile found in his lips.</hi> All others
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19937:40"/>are comprehended under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſin, which they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put off while they are clad in theſe <hi>robes of fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt of <hi>Gods Saints</hi> have had their ſlips and fals, and to make them flye forth from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to a better and ſurer hold, they have had often remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their owne weakeneſſe, in many grievous wounds, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter derelictions, have often fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, been wounded with the <hi>weak reed</hi> of their owne ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Wonder not then if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a <hi>David</hi> defiling his hands and heart with innocent blood,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.9</note> and unlawfull pleaſures. <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.5</note> though a <hi>man after Gods owne heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.14.</note> was but a man. Wonder not to behold a <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 3.12</note> the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt among the ſonnes of men, committing a double whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 11.1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Spirituall and Corporall; Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> though ſo wiſe, was but a man. Wonder not that <hi>Peter</hi> ſo foully denyed and abjur'd <hi>his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar 14.66 67, &amp;c.</note>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:19937:41"/>unleſſe you wonder that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was a man.</p>
            <p>We receive with our birth and nature, two inevitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; <hi>peccare &amp; mori, to ſin and to dye.</hi> And though it hath beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the piety of the <hi>Churches</hi> children to juſtifie the <hi>Patriarkes</hi> againſt the bitter taunts of <hi>ſcaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing I ſhmaelites, and uncircumciſed Philiſtines,</hi> and like the <hi>good ſons of Noah, to go backward with</hi> the vail of charity in their hands,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.23.</note> and <hi>cover the nakedneſſe of their fathers:</hi> yet muſt not that <hi>vaile</hi> of charity blindfold our judgement, ſo that we altogether deny thoſe faults to be, which we would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed from the ſcorne of irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men. <hi>Diminuit culpam excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio, non tollit. God</hi> would have the errours and faults of his Saints as well to ſtand upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, as their vertues; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Seneca Nat. quaeſt. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>23</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayes of <hi>Alexander</hi> his murther of <hi>Caliſthenes: hoc eſt Alexand. crimen aeternum quod
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19937:41"/>nulla virtus, nulla bellorum faelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas redim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> This is a blemiſh that ſhall eternally ſticke on <hi>his</hi> faire name, which no vertue of <hi>his,</hi> nor the glory of all <hi>his</hi> victories ſhall redeeme: <hi>quoties enim quis dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; occidit Perſarum multa mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, opponetur &amp; Caliſthenem: quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties dictum erit occidit Darium, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponetur &amp; Caliſthenem; quoties om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Oceano tenus vicit, ipſum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tentavit &amp; imperium, &amp;c. op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponetur ſed occidit Calisthenem.</hi> As often as it ſhall be ſaid, he ſlew many thouſands of <hi>Perſians,</hi> yea but it ſhall be ſaid againe, he ſlew <hi>Caliſthenes:</hi> As oft as it ſhall be ſaid, he conquered <hi>Darius,</hi> yea but he kill'd <hi>Caliſthenes:</hi> As often as it ſhall be reported to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne of his name, he ſubdued all to the very <hi>Ocean,</hi> and it too, and removed his Kingdome from a corner of <hi>Thrace,</hi> till it knew no other bounds, but the ſame with the whole earth; but, as a check to all his glory, it ſhall be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19937:42"/>ſaid, yea but he kill'd <hi>Calisthenes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it is in the bleſſed Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with many of the <hi>Lords wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies,</hi> whoſe religious life and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity deſervedly cals upon our wonder to behold them: but then againe, leſt they of themſelves ſhould entertaine too high an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, or we of them — <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinit in piſcem,</hi> ſome frailty or foul ſlip like <hi>Philip's</hi> boy tels them, <hi>they are but men,</hi> ſubject to like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities as we are, ſinne it ſelfe not excepted. No marvell then if we finde <hi>righteous Lots</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt Gods counſell and direction, guilty of weaknes and folly, for all his confidence in his <hi>Behold now, this City is neere to flee unto, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seest thou a man wiſe in his owne conceit? there is more hope of a foole than of ſuch a man</hi> (Saith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>) Prov. 26.12. The opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our owne wiſedome is the greateſt argument of our folly <hi>Multi</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) <hi>pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19937:42"/>ad ſapientiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>niſi put aſſent ſe perveniſſe:</hi> many men had been wiſe, if they had not beene too wiſe; and if they had not preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves with the ſwolne dropſie of ſelfe-opinion, had made a wholſome growth in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid wiſedome. Many men had gone farre, if they had not look't backe on their progreſſe, in a multiplying glaſſe, and ſo thought they had gone farre al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
            <p>This overweening conceit of our owne knowledge, as in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learning, ſo eſpecially in the height of <hi>divine ſpeculation,</hi> things (I meane) which tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend the reach of reaſon, is moſt dangerous. I dare in thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a <hi>faith implicite,</hi> and prefer <hi>caecam obedientiam &amp; fidem, the blind and budling faith of Papiſts,</hi> before the moſt nice and oculate of the moſt learned. Credulity there takes the place of reaſon, and that, without uſurpation:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19937:43"/>where we have a <hi>new Logicke,</hi> and <hi>authority becomes the best argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> To oppugne <hi>Gods</hi> truth or counſell with our reaſon, is no leſſe than the extremity of folly, and impudence: we muſt deny our reaſon, become fooliſh, nay abſurd to our owne wiſedome, believe above, againſt it.</p>
            <p>To defend <hi>Gods</hi> truth or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell with our reaſon or argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is a fooliſh and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted zeale, and which acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth more queſtion our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than commend our zeale. Though the <hi>Arke of Gods</hi> truth ſeeme to us to be <hi>ſhaken</hi> by the oppoſers and enemies of it, ſo that it appeare to be in <hi>danger of falling,</hi> yet ought not we to be ſo indiſcreetly zealous,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.6, 7.</note> with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zah, to uphold it</hi> with the <hi>weake hand</hi> of our reaſon. Our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is then beſt, when it ſeemes moſt abſurd: when it lookes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the authority of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, and yet that without
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19937:43"/>more examination concludes an equity of the command.</p>
            <p>It was the triumph of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.18 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>that above, againſt hope he beleeved God, when Sara's womb was now dead.</hi> It was the triumph of his obedience to be ready to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God, in ſacrificing of his <hi>own and onely ſonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.10</note> when nature and reaſon had the faireſt plea that could be againſt it, and might judge it unnaturall, unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, monſtrous and wicked. But he look't rather to the <hi>author</hi> than <hi>matter</hi> of the command, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured not the juſtice of the action by the rule of reaſon, but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the reaſon of his obedience in the will, power and juſtice of <hi>him who</hi> commanded, <hi>who</hi> is a law to <hi>himſelfe</hi> and to all others.</p>
            <p>It had beene well with <hi>Lot,</hi> if his <hi>obedience,</hi> his <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the firſt to Gods authority commanding, the ſecond to his wiſedome directing, the laſt to Gods mercy delivering, had
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19937:44"/>made him follow the Angels di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and <hi>gone unto the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine:</hi> but while he will be ſo wiſe to teach his teacher, <hi>God</hi> ſhewes him his folly by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and makes <hi>the mountaine,</hi> which (if he had gone when <hi>God</hi> bid him) a place of ſafety, God (I ſay) makes it afterward (when he goes on his own errand) the place of his puniſhment.</p>
            <p>You have heard before <hi>Lots ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative requeſt,</hi> with the reaſons of it, <hi>not ſo my Lord, for I cannot.</hi> Now it remaines that we come more particularly to handle his <hi>affirmative requeſt,</hi> and reaſons of it. <hi>O let me eſcape thither; to Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>affirmative requeſt</hi> we obſerved, Firſt the <hi>order</hi> of it, and Secondly <hi>the matter</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The order</hi> of it, that it comes in the rere of his arguments, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the lee and ſhelter of them, we will therefore reſerve to it the laſt place, and here firſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19937:44"/>take notice of his <hi>Aſteriske or note of attention before</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayes his confidence in the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his requeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold now,</hi> ſayes <hi>Lot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How weake is our wiſedome, yet how ſtrong our confidence and opinion? yet obſtinacie and pride beare up our opinions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt God himſelfe, ſo that with a ſawcy preſumption, we dare capitulate and indent with him, nay even chalk him out the way with a <hi>not ſo, for I cannot but behold now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When man lookes through the <hi>falſe medium</hi> of his <hi>owne affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and paſſion,</hi> what monſtrous errours and <hi>ſoleciſmes</hi> doth he count? The <hi>intellective</hi> part of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> is like a cleare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſturbed fountaine, wherein the <hi>forme</hi> of things is truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented: but when once the <hi>affections</hi> (which are the <hi>muddy and earthy parts of the ſoule</hi>) are
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19937:45"/>ſtirred up, it becomes a dirtie puddle, wherein things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented <hi>blindly, lamely, and falſely.</hi> The <hi>istericke eye</hi> wonders that others ſee not all things yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low as it ſelfe does, and calls that others blindneſſe, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed its own infirmitie. <hi>This City is new.</hi> Yea 'tis ſo <hi>neer</hi> thy affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that a <hi>juſt diſtance</hi> being wanting <hi>(a condition of perfect ſight)</hi> thine eye muſt needs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit an errour. If <hi>God</hi> therefore <hi>behold,</hi> he ſhall but ſee thy errour, rather then any thing that may move him to condeſcend to thy requeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold now.</hi> Why, as though thou ſaw ſomething that <hi>God</hi> ſaw not, or as though <hi>He</hi> that had power to deliver thee, could want wiſdome to direct thee, but <hi>He</hi> muſt be directed by thee, with a <hi>not ſo my Lord, but behold now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that made the eye ſhall not be ſee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 94.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>He</hi> that made the ſoule and inveſted it with that noble
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19937:45"/>and royall facultie of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſhall not <hi>He</hi> underſtand?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Natura agit per line as breviores,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Phyloſophy</hi>). <hi>Nature</hi> is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuperfluous in her actions, but goes the neereſt and moſt compendious way to worke, and ſhall the <hi>God of nature,</hi> not doe ſo much more?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God is in Heaven and thou on the Earth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) if then <hi>He</hi> hath the advantage of the ground,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.2.</note> as much as the heaven is higher then the earth, needs <hi>He</hi> to be lifted up on the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of us dwarfes? needs that Sunne of light our candle, that Ocean our ſpoonefull, or that <hi>firſt intelligence</hi> our information or direction of <hi>not ſo my Lord, but behold now?</hi> muſt <hi>He</hi> be behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thee for thy <hi>behold now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold now.</hi> Why? as if <hi>God</hi> ſaw as man ſaw. Our <hi>eye</hi> is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by <hi>darkeneſſe,</hi> by <hi>diſtance,</hi> by <hi>interpoſure</hi> of a groſſe body. Being not hindered, what ſees it,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19937:46"/>but colour? It is terminated in the outward <hi>ſurface</hi> and <hi>ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> never penetrating into the inmoſt and retired eſſence. But <hi>Gods eye</hi> is not as mans, neither doth <hi>He</hi> looke as man looketh. Within, without, hidden, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, darke, light, are words, and things, to which onely mans weakneſſe hath given a being; to <hi>that eye of the world</hi> there are no ſuch <hi>diſtinctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then (for a word of uſe) let us ſee the vanitie of many men, who think with the colour of an excuſe (which our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hath unskilfully doubted) to bleare the eyes of that <hi>all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning wiſedome,</hi> to which <hi>thoughts</hi> themſelves (things of weakeſt eſſence and neereſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) <hi>are open and apparent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.13. Pſal. 139.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>From the <hi>Aſteriske</hi> and note of attention <hi>behold now</hi> I come to <hi>Lots reaſons</hi> to urge his <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative requeſt,</hi> which argue more the good mans affection, then
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19937:46"/>enforce his concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocenti a melior est quam elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quintilian.</note> Innocence (ſaith <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian</hi>) is better then eloquence and a good cauſe then a good Orator. <hi>Magna eſt veritas &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valebit.</hi> O there's a conſidence in truth, better then all the flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> all the proofes of reaſon. Each colour implies ſome defect, and each proofe ſome doubt, that doubt, a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie of the contrary. And therefore it hath uſually beene the guiſe of innocence to make no argument her beſt argument, and the ſlight of reaſon, the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why ſhe ſhould not be ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>It was a brave and heroicke ſcorne in the <hi>Affrican Scipio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus Livi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> when being accuſed of treaſon againſt the common wealth, he (in ſtead of anſwering) led the people to the Temple to give thankes for that renowned vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory (that day twelve moneths
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19937:47"/>before) by him obtained. <hi>Scipio's</hi> vertue ſcorned to bee defended, let his actions not words ſpeake for him. And me thinkes more could not have been ſaid for <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio</hi> then this ſilence, and his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine of defence did out doe all oratorie. And verily truth (like a <hi>perfect cube</hi>) needs not theſe poore props: let falſehood and a weake cauſe ſtrengthen their weake credit with theſe merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, that like Tartars or Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers will be hired to either ſide for the better pay. <hi>For indeed our corrupted reaſon is become the onely advocate to paſſion and affection;</hi> and ſo vaſſatized unto them, that as it is the greateſt of our taskes, ſo is it that, wherein ſhe ſhewes the beſt of her abilities, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good the moſt deſperate and forlorne cauſe.</p>
            <p>Our affections firſt reſolve, and then make reaſon harrow all the <hi>Topicks of invention,</hi> to finde defences, if not excuſes, uſing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19937:47"/>herein poore reaſon as a great <hi>Potentate</hi> not long a goe his cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. For having a deſire to marry within degrees unlawfull, he ſet his learned men on worke to prove it lawfull, and againe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a while (being cloy'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring change) ſet them againe on worke to prove the former mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage unlawfull.</p>
            <p>Nay! ſo monſtrous is the folly of our credulitie, when our affections claime a ſtrong inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the cauſe, that the ſame arguments ſhall ſerve us to prove <hi>contradictions,</hi> yea and the ſame reaſons perſwade or confirme the lawfullneſſe of that, which in themſelves prove it moſt unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe the words of my Text, with the two precedent verſes, in which <hi>Lot</hi> would prove <hi>Gods</hi> Counſell as full of danger as his owne of convenience and ſafety, when as all the reaſons he can alleadge, prove the flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:19937:48"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt, <hi>This Citie is neere to flye unto and it is a little one. This Citie.</hi>] Is it a <hi>Citie</hi> and not the more likely to be ſinfull? It is <hi>Bela, a Citie of the Plaines,</hi> and not more likely to be in the ſame manner and degree ſinfull?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly is it <hi>neere Sodom</hi> and not the more dangerous? nay is it <hi>neere</hi> as well in condition as place? how much more likely to be joyned in puniſhment?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly <hi>is it little?</hi> how much more reaſon to be deſtroy'd? For ſaith <hi>God to Jonah ſhould not I then ſpare this great Citie Nineveh, wherein are more then ſixeſcore thouſand perſons, that cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne betwixt their right hand and their left, and alſo much cattle. Jonah</hi> 4.11. How contrary is <hi>Gods</hi> argument to <hi>Lots? God</hi> will have a <hi>Citie</hi> ſpared becauſe it is <hi>great, Lot</hi> becauſe <hi>it is little.</hi> But theſe rich and fruitfull plaines had much endeared the heart of the good <hi>Patriarch:</hi> loath he
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19937:48"/>was to change <hi>a Citie,</hi> and a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous valley for a <hi>mountainous and rockie deſert,</hi> and therefore though <hi>God</hi> be his immediate Counſellor, the end his ſafety, yet being intereſted by affection, againſt the authoritie of his <hi>Lord,</hi> the dutie of a <hi>ſervant,</hi> the mercie of a <hi>deliverer,</hi> doth <hi>Lot</hi> ſtruggle firſt by delayes, and then with forced reaſon to prove <hi>Gods</hi> Counſell full of danger, as his own requeſt of conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency and ſafety. Nay ſo farre hath his affection blinded him, worſe then the <hi>Sodomites at his doore,</hi> for they could not ſee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Angels blinded them, <hi>Lot</hi> could not ſee when the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels directed him.</p>
            <p>I think miſguided, unſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reaſon, doth rather breed ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitions then cleere them. <hi>Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes</hi> never compounded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, ſeldome the law friends. There is indeed an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted Logicke,</hi> which preſcribes
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19937:49"/>
               <hi>formes and motions,</hi> but follow it into the practice of men, it hath ſtill <hi>one terme more then it ſhould, affection or paſſion.</hi> The Lawyer hath not he his <hi>rationem tinnulam</hi> for his <hi>quartum argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum?</hi> and what wonder then if in a double ſence he commit <hi>fallaciam in quatuor terminis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it thus onely in our every dayes actions and occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, which according to our intereſt reaſon muſt juſtifie or at leaſt excuſe, but as if that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>circle of Arts,</hi> had made them mad too with walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in it, the <hi>Schooles</hi> themſelves and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> have <hi>matricu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated</hi> the ſame dotage. Who would not unſtudie reaſon and befoole all arguments, that ſhould ſee a <hi>theſis affirmative</hi> proved by many reaſons, his true <hi>Negative</hi> proved alſo, yet both anſwered, and after a long pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe with inquiſition and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, arrive fairely at the ſame
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19937:49"/>point where it begun, and end in the greater doubt? <hi>Quid leo eſt, niſi inſanire cum ratione?</hi> Whats this but to be a learned foole, and with great labour to make Cob-webs to be ſwept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way? <hi>Magno conatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nugas!</hi> Would not this <hi>(under things of faith)</hi> be enough to make a man a <hi>Skeptick?</hi> Sure we need not, to the native weakneſſe of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and reaſon make it more wretched by this ſlavery, and mancipation to our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and paſſions, unleſſe to a weake eye we would throw in duſt. But I leave them in their maze and come to <hi>Lots</hi> arguments themſelves to enforce his requeſt, and firſt of the <hi>object of his behold;</hi> the firſt reaſon of <hi>Lots</hi> affirmative requeſt, being <hi>à qualitate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Citie, 'tis a Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which (as in the reſt of his arguments) I might propoſe to my ſelfe this order. Every argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19937:50"/>or reaſon hath <hi>veritatem or veritatis ſpeciem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt then I might ſhew the probabilitie of his argument.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the fallacie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we might draw from either ſome uſe for our ſelves, I might thus improve the matter of my text unto a large com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, if I ſhould dilate particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> on every of his arguments.</p>
            <p>As firſt in this firſt argument that it is <hi>a Citie</hi> the other <hi>a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> I might ſhew you in this one three ſeverall motives to <hi>Lots</hi> deſire, <hi>Plentie, Societie,</hi> and <hi>Safetie.</hi> Then in anſwering theſe againe, I might (without being <hi>Heterogeneall</hi>) dilate upon the commendation of their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites <hi>Povertie</hi> and <hi>Solitarineſſe,</hi> each of which beſides the true determining and moderating of our deſire of theſe, might ſuffice to hold diſcourſe beyond the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of your patience. But I
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19937:50"/>ſhall content my ſelfe to glance at ſome of theſe, rather then to tye your patience in a long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt then of <hi>Lots firſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This Citie.</hi> Tis a Citie, the other a rude and barren <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Citie</hi> was before time cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bela</hi> as appeareth out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.8. untill this occaſion of <hi>Lots</hi> requeſt, and the reaſon of it, altered the name to <hi>Zoar,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>little,</hi> becauſe he ſaid <hi>it is a little one, and is it not a little one?</hi> It was one of the <hi>five Cities of the Plaines,</hi> called <hi>the Plaines of Jordan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.10.</note> a Valley wherein nature prevented the labour of the induſtrious hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, in a voluntarie and unbought fruitfulneſſe, ſo that it needed not to be watered with the ſweat of induſtry to make it fruitfull, but of it ſelfe yeclded to the inhabitants occaſion of idleneſſe, to the neighbours of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19937:51"/>envy, and to all of wonder. Such a place it was, that it grew to a word exemplary to ſet forth the pride and height of fruitfulneſſe. <hi>It was watered like the Garden of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>and like the plaines of Jordan before the Lord deſtroyed Sodom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here were then three ſtrong attractives to <hi>Lots</hi> deſire, <hi>Plentie, Societie, and Safetie,</hi> and in <hi>this Citie</hi> all theſe three concurre to make life ſecurely happy. Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of wealth and delicacies to refreſh the body, abundance of company to delight and cheer the minde, and then ſafety which onely makes the other conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate in the ſecuritie to enjoy them.</p>
            <p>For plentie and riches it is true that <hi>Quintillan</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">Quint. dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoribus. pag. <hi>689.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias facilius eſt ut invenias qui vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuperet quam qui contempſerit.</hi> Its eaſier to finde a man that will diſpaire them, then that will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe them, one that can <hi>in the Schooles</hi> wittily <hi>declaime</hi> againſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19937:51"/>them, rather then one that will diſclaime them. <hi>Quis niſi mentis inops?</hi> he ſhall preſently be begd for a foole. To ſtand in tire upon his owne bottome and not need to be beholding to any, nay to have all that which ſhall hold all others either in his friendſhip or ſlavery. O it is <hi>ſupremum morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis votum, &amp; locus diis proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> it is the higheſt condition mortality can be capeable of, and riches give it. Moſt of the ſtudies, inventions, toiles, travels and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings of men aime at this one end, <hi>to be rich.</hi> Heaven it ſelf is but too often made the price of this purchaſe: Men goe there to fetch gold, where they looſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and day; <hi>itum eſt viſcera ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi> into the bowels of the earth; deeper, into hell. This <hi>Image of Caeſar</hi> cauſeth an univerſall i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, and to that ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all ſubſcribe.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Lot</hi> then, ſhould deſire to go to <hi>this Citie,</hi> rather then to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19937:52"/>a barren and naked mountaine, we need not wonder, unleſſe we wonder that men preferre plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before poverty. I ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly idle to make more words of ſo confeſs'd a theme.</p>
            <p>In that it <hi>is a City</hi> there is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond attractive, <hi>Society,</hi> and that is to man as his owne element. <hi>Society</hi> is the life of our life, and ſolitarineſſe is a very living bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall. I might here move a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem, why men naturally in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and ſilent retirements and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes finde a kinde of horror and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightfulneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it that as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes of <hi>friends,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov 27.17.</note> 
               <hi>they ſtrengthen the faces one of another,</hi> ſo our <hi>Genius</hi> doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a mutuall comfort and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood from one anothers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſo in this ſolitude (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the <hi>rayes and circle of their vertue</hi>) acknowledges that want in this weakneſſe?</p>
            <p>Or doth the <hi>ſoule</hi> apprehend the <hi>preſence of ſome good or evill ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:19937:52"/>which are both ready, the one to offend, the other to defend us?</p>
            <p>Or is it the <hi>reflexe of our owne conſcience upon it ſelfe,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty of ſinne, muſt needs be of feare?</p>
            <p>Or is it <hi>antipathy of nature,</hi> which in this ſees a <hi>praeludium</hi> of that <hi>univerſall ſilence to which all go downe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Siquis aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate ea eſt ut congreſſ us &amp; ſocieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num fugiat &amp; oderit, qualem fuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Athenis. Timonem neſcio quem accepim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, tamen is pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti non poſſit, ut non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirat ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem apud quem, &amp;c, Cicero de Amic fol. <hi>220</hi> vide, ſi plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t plura ibid.</note> What the reaſon of it is, I know not, thus much I am ſure of, that this horror is an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent argument, that man is <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum animal,</hi> that in his nature is implanted a love of <hi>Society,</hi> and that he was as well made for <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as Cities</hi> for him; ſo that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorites</hi> and <hi>Hermits</hi> are gone as farre from mans nature, as they are from his company.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timon</hi> himſelfe, that greateſt <hi>Owle of Athens,</hi> and <hi>prodigie of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that profeſs'd an <hi>antipathy</hi> to all man, nay, to all humanity, yet he (for all his doggedneſſe) as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> wittily ſayes of him) could
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19937:53"/>not <hi>carere hominum conſortio, apud quos virus acerbitatis ſuae evome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> he could not want the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men, though it were but to ſpit the poyſon of his gall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now for <hi>Lots</hi> third <hi>attractive</hi> to the <hi>City,</hi> which is <hi>ſafety,</hi> that man ſhould deſire it; needs no more proofe, than that a man loves himſelfe, and it were vaine in me to go about to prove it.</p>
            <p>Here then were ſeeming rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to juſtifie the lawfulneſſe of his requeſt, and excuſe his unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to obey God's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. But,</p>
            <p>From the ſpecious ſhew and waight of thoſe arguments, I come to the fallacie in them: and for anſwer in generall to all, firſt <hi>by conceſſion;</hi> ſay, 'tis true, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, that <hi>this being a City,</hi> is more convenient to <hi>fly unto,</hi> more comfortable to <hi>reſt in,</hi> there are thoſe invitations here which in the <hi>mountaines</hi> are not. But
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19937:53"/>what then? muſt <hi>God</hi> be obeyed only with our conveniency, and the condition of our ſervice be our owne content? What is this but to make <hi>Gods</hi> of our ſelves, and to obſerve <hi>him</hi> only whilſt he will pleaſure us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Egregiam vero laudem?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgil.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How much better did <hi>afflicted Job:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Shall we receive good at Gods hands, and ſhall we not receive evill?</hi> What if <hi>God</hi> commanded thee, not to danger, but to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine loſſe of thy content, thy eſtate, nay thy life, wilt thou not obey? Is not <hi>he</hi> the <hi>ſupreame arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life and death? He</hi> that gave thee all, may <hi>be</hi> not therefore command all thou art owner of? Muſt our reaſon, or will, or content be <hi>check-maſter</hi> with <hi>his</hi> ſupreame authority, and our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience be limited to our profit, our pleaſure, or ſuch reſpects?</p>
            <p>Yet 'tis thus alas, many times with many amongſt us. <hi>God</hi> hath many that ſeeme <hi>his</hi> ſervants,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19937:54"/>who are indeed but their owne: men that follow him, but 'tis like the <hi>Jewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.26.</note> 
               <hi>for the meats ſake onely,</hi> becauſe <hi>proſperity, riches and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour are friends with religion,</hi> and go along with it: let <hi>theſe</hi> part, and <hi>Religion</hi> take one way, and proſperity another, theſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants will ſoone acknowledge their maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion</hi> had never worſe friends than when it had moſt, and never ſo many, as when the <hi>temporall</hi> ſword joynes with the <hi>Spirituall.</hi> The warme and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Sun-ſhine of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces many <hi>aequivocall births,</hi> that peſter the <hi>Church</hi> wherein they are, ſuch as are imperfect crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in reſpect of true generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe though they are in the <hi>Church,</hi> yet are they not of it, they ſeeme to hearken (with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) to <hi>Gods</hi> voyce, but it is while it ſounds to their eares in a <hi>pleaſing key;</hi> while their profit, their pleaſure or reputation run
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19937:54"/>in <hi>paralells</hi> with religion, they hold the ſame courſe with <hi>Gods</hi> children, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe part, the bias of their reſpects drawes theſe crooked, theſe turne too, to the left hand after their ſiniſter ends. Let God command them to go, if it be to that which croſſes not their deſires, they runne with the formoſt, like a ſtone downe a hill: but to any diſconvenience, diſcommodity or diſcredit (as <hi>Lot</hi> here <hi>to the mountaine</hi>) O that's up hill, againſt the haire to them, then <hi>O not ſo my Lord,</hi> they then <hi>cannot,</hi> leſt ſome of <hi>theſe evils take them, and they die;</hi> a thouſand ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, a thouſand pretences of feares and evils that may <hi>take them,</hi> ſhall ſtand in their way, and you ſhall beare <hi>I cannot, lest ſome evill take me and I dye.</hi> But if <hi>God</hi> will command them where their affection drawes, let them go that way, none more forward in their obedience, their owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects and deſires being the <hi>maine
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19937:55"/>ſpring</hi> from which proceeds their <hi>motion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I might ſecondly anſwer, (eſpecially of the two firſt) from the nature of them, they heing <hi>adiapbora,</hi> things indifferent, that in themſelves are neither good nor evill, cannot, ought not to be deſired without <hi>Gods</hi> commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to enjoy them. But I leave this, and paſſe to the ſecond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall argument, which is a <hi>quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate viae, this City is neere to flye unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis neere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Eaſe</hi> is a great flatterer of our nature, and difficultie, at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall diſtance from our affection with danger. Labour is the price of honor, and great and heroick ſpirits only the purchaſers. The i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle wiſhes of the ſluggard, nor the faint reſolutions of the cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, will never arrive at that height where honour dwels. A ſpirit that growes big as the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger does, and gathers as it grows,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19937:55"/>ſhall attaine the true greatneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly <hi>'tis neere,</hi> and ſo might befriend his <hi>curioſity,</hi> that though he were forbidden <hi>to looke backe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.17</note> yet he might from hence ſee whether and how <hi>Sodom</hi> ſhould be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curioſity</hi> is an itch of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which we would have claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though with a poyſonous naile. 'Tis a diſeaſe we are all ſicke of. <hi>Our firſt parents ſet their childrens teeth on edge</hi> with that ſowre apple (which their firſt <hi>curioſity</hi> to be like <hi>gods</hi> in knowledge,<note place="margin">Gen 3 6.</note> to know good and evill, made them taſte) that ſowre apple (I ſay) hath ever ſince <hi>ſet their childrens teeth on edge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.2 Gen. 3.7.</note> Yet they had <hi>their eyes ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</hi> and what ſaw they? nothing, <hi>a privation that they were naked.</hi> They ſaw much like the bleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey'd woman in the <hi>Fable,</hi> that had covenanted with the Phyſitian, to give him ſo much money when he had reſtored her to perfect
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19937:56"/>ſight. The Phyſitian at every viſit ſtole away ſome of her houſhold ſtuffe, till at laſt all was gone: by which time being cured, and he demanding his reward, ſhe tels him ſhe now ſaw worſe then ever, for whereas before ſhe ſaw her houſefull of goods, ſhe now could ſee <hi>juſt nothing.</hi> Their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie and deſire of divine knowledge brought them juſt to ſuch a paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their eyes were opened,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.7.</note> but what ſaw they? <hi>That they were naked.</hi> Whereas before they were inveſted with many divine and noble faculties, many rich attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and priviledges of ſoule and body, they now ſaw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſroabed, naked and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably deſtitute of all thoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their eyes were opened,</hi> and what ſaw they? Even much like the blinde man in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 8.24.</note> 
               <hi>men like trees,</hi> mankinde degenerated into an inferiour kinde, violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurred with his paſſions, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19937:56"/>
               <hi>become as the brute beaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.12.20.</note> ſtupid as the block or tree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Curioſitie</hi> is often puniſhed like jealouſie. The impatience of the deſire is one torture, and it often findes a ſecond in the object it ſeekes. It many times fiſhes for a Serpent, or would try the dangerous concluſion to kill a baſiliske.</p>
            <p>Such a <hi>Curioſitie,</hi> was in <hi>the men of Bethſhemiſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 6.19.</note> and it was a deare one, of whom <hi>fifty thouſand threeſcore and ten men</hi> forfeited not their eyes onely but their lives, for <hi>prying into the Arke of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a <hi>Curioſitie</hi> was in <hi>Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> the laſt King of the <hi>Goths in Spaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L. Verulam</hi> his eſſay of Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and it was a deere one, when he would burſt open a part of his palace, which the religion of many ages kept untouched: and what found he? Pictures of the <hi>Moores</hi> with a propheſie, that when that part of the palace was opened, the people there reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19937:57"/>ſhould conquer <hi>Spaine,</hi> as indeed under <hi>Muſae</hi> and <hi>Tarif</hi> they preſently did.</p>
            <p>Such a <hi>Curioſitie</hi> was in <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey the great,</hi> and it was a deare one. Vpon the conquering of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not long before our <hi>Saviours</hi> birth, though ſtoutly oppoſed and threatned by the Prieſts, he would needs enter into the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum.</hi> And what ſaw he to feed his <hi>Curioſity?</hi> Nothing but as <hi>Tacitus</hi> in his hiſtorie tells us,<note place="margin">Tacitus lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nulla intus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, effigie vacuam ſedem &amp; ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia arcana:</hi> there was no picture or image of <hi>God,</hi> it was not like the painted Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what followed upon this? —<hi>ex illo</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Res illi fluere &amp; retro ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſa referri,</hi> ſome ſuch thing met him as did <hi>Brutus</hi> afterwards that dampned and flatted his undaunted courage. And it is worth the obſerving, that from that time things ever went
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19937:57"/>downe the winde, in all his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings the ſprightlineſſe of his great and fortunate <hi>Genius</hi> forſook him, and grew faint and cowardly.</p>
            <p>It was none of the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations that <hi>Tacitus</hi> gives of <hi>Agrippa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacitus in vita Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colae. pag. <hi>656.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>retinuitque</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod eſt difficilimum ſapientiae modum,</hi> he ſet limits to his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome it ſelfe, and preſcribed a <hi>non ultra</hi> to his deſire of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And it is the <hi>Symtome</hi> of a well man'd temper, to be able to reclaime our unſatiate eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and take of the edge of our deſire to know.</p>
            <p>It is in <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> as in other hils, there is an height to which we may let our ſelves aſpire: but ſome there are that thinke, that height muſt reach heaven it ſelfe, and ſtrive this way to enter into <hi>Gods</hi> Cloſet. That old itch of our firſt parents <hi>to be like Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 3.</note> 
               <hi>to know good and evill,</hi> they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver claw of. But there is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19937:58"/>an height to which we may goe, but he that reſts not there, may goe further, but it is downewards, and that many times <hi>impotente ſui pondere,</hi> with a ſwinge that cannot controule it ſelfe, till it carry him head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into the dangerous preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice of diſtraction and errour. Such while like <hi>Elias</hi> they are wrapt in the <hi>Chariot</hi> of contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation,<note place="margin">2 King 2.11.13.</note> reach not to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect viſion of the heavens, and things done and enacted there (which they aſpire to) but they <hi>let fall their mantles</hi> which ſhould vaile their nakedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Knowledge, as it is in it ſelfe, is a ſweet thing, but it hath its ſower ſauce with it. Like Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar it doth not ſo much ſatisfie the appetite, as whet it with a new and freſh deſire. The <hi>Satyre</hi> that could not be content to ſee the fire, but muſt needs in <hi>Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſitie</hi> feele it, ſcorched his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:19937:58"/>
            <p>Now for anſwer to this ſecond argument of <hi>Lots,</hi> and to ſhew the <hi>fallacie</hi> of it, whereas he ſaith <hi>it is neer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>neerneſſe</hi> is ſo farre from making lawfull his requeſt that it ſhewes it rather to be abſurd: for if it be <hi>neer Sodom,</hi> it is neer danger, and the more being as <hi>neer</hi> in condition as in place. Is this <hi>Zoar</hi> a Citie of the Plaines, and not in the ſame condition of ſinfulneſſe with <hi>Sodom?</hi> Then <hi>Lot</hi> thou wouldeſt change place but not company, and the next degree to ſinne is to be in the company of ſinners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Woe be to him that is alone</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) and yet (ſay I) better it is to be alone then in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſinners,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.10.</note> and that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of a double danger <hi>infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of <hi>infection,</hi> for (I dare <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſay) it is as great a miracle, for a man that permits himſelfe the libertie of wicked ſocietie not to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19937:59"/>be tainted,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.27.</note> as for the <hi>three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the fiery furnace,</hi> not to be burned. And good reaſon is therefor this, ſince in our body there is not ſo great a diſpoſition to catch fire, as in our ſoules to receive the tincture of ſinne. The cuſtomarie beholding of ſin committed, (though by others) doth in our ſelves weaken the ſtrength of our <hi>Antipathy,</hi> and by little and little familiarize it to our nature, bringing us by an <hi>inſenſible progreſſion,</hi> from a <hi>full hatred</hi> to a <hi>faint diſlike,</hi> from <hi>diſlike to a toleration,</hi> from a <hi>tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to a conſent,</hi> ſo to a <hi>delight,</hi> and at laſt to a <hi>ſocietie and actuall commiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And as the danger of <hi>infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is much, ſo ſecondly little leſſe is the danger of <hi>judgement.</hi> Witneſſe <hi>Lot</hi> himſelf, who ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the captivity of <hi>Sodom,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſo journed in the Citie of <hi>Sodom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tum tua res agitur paries
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19937:59"/>cum proximus ardet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgil.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Who deſires a vicinitie with danger? Firſt therefore looke unto thy ſafety, and then to thine eaſe. <hi>'Tis neer</hi> to <hi>Sodom,</hi> and therefore farre from ſafetie. He commits a ſtrange <hi>ſoloeciſme</hi> that makes the way his end, that lookes how he goes, not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Such is the folly of us wretched men. Doe not we juſt as <hi>Lot</hi> did? When the ſeeming pleaſures of the way cozen us into hell, when fooliſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with the <hi>pleaſures of ſin for a time we goe on in the wayes of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>as an Oxe goeth on to the ſlaughter, or as a foole to the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſtockes, till a dart ſtrik through our liver: as a bird haſteth to the ſnare, and knoweth not that it is for his life. Prov.</hi> 7.22, 23.27.</p>
            <p>Thus much for <hi>Lots</hi> firſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>à quantitate viae, it is neer.</hi> I proceed to the ſecond <hi>à quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate termini, tis little, it is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle one,</hi> and is it not <hi>perexigua, a very little one?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:19937:60"/>
            <p>In which words (me thinkes) I diſcerne as much paſſion as hope of compaſſion. <hi>Behold it is a little one, and is it not a little one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me (with your patience) before I enter further into exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the argument (doe what I thinke the words will give me leave) looke over the <hi>pale of Divinitie,</hi> into the groves and ſhades of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and there would I deſire the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>probleme: Why men have a kinde of naturall indulgence and delight in little things? Or why men are more taken with things that are under their juſt and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary proportion then thoſe that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>inanimate</hi> it is not onely not ſo, but directly contrary, where with the <hi>quantitie of bulke</hi> is alſo encreaſed the <hi>quantity of vertue,</hi> as in <hi>pearles, precious ſtones</hi> and the like.</p>
            <p>But for <hi>artificiall things,</hi> 'tis
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19937:60"/>indeed many times on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that the valew and eſteeme of them is ſo much the more, by how much they are the leſſe. To comprehend in the compaſſe of a Wall-nut, or in a leſſe quantitie, ſo many ſeverall ſprings, wheeles, catches, motions, all diſtinctly, regularly moving, is it not farre more admirable, then the <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar</hi> of the ſame in a great clock? For our eſteeme of theſe leſſer workes, the reaſon is evident, in regard it ſhewes the more art, to contrive a worke in the leſſe quantitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Materiam ſuperabit opus</hi>— Nay this is grounded upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note place="margin">Ovid.</note> which <hi>nunquam abundat in ſupervacaneis, ſed agit per lineas breviores,</hi> goes the moſt compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and neer way to work.</p>
            <p>But now for <hi>animated</hi> things, why we are more tenderly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards them in their <hi>minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and infancie</hi> rather then in their <hi>adult-age and maturitie:</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:19937:61"/>What may be the reaſon of that?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Is it that innocency of theirs, with which we are affected, that yet is defiled with no other ſin, then what by the neceſſity of their procreation is contracted to them?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Or is it from a nobleneſſe of nature to be indulgent towards them that are unable to helpe themſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Or is it, we love them as the meanes of our eternitie, to which we aſpire by this renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Or will you ſay it is a weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our judgements, and miſplacing of our affections on the imperfection and inchoation of the creature rather then on their adult-age and perfection?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Or is it a kinde of ſimpathy with our owne principles?</p>
            <p>Sure if it be none of theſe, and that I may erre in the reaſon, yet the thing it ſelf is evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that naturally we are more compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19937:61"/>indulgent to the infancy and minoritie of the creatures, then to them in their adult-age and maturitie, and our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> himſelfe ſeemes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in <hi>his owne</hi> example this affection as lawfull as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>in taking little children in his armes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>laying his hands upon them and bleſſing them, rebuking thoſe that forbade them to be brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him,</hi> and many ſuch like paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages.</p>
            <p>But I am afraid I have dwelt too long on this <hi>theme,</hi> though I am confident, not with any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencie to my Text, in which I finde the ſtraines of like paſſionate indulgence, <hi>it is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle one, and is it not a little one and my ſoule ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I proceed to examine the argument, and firſt of the <hi>proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie</hi> of it, and ſecondly of the <hi>fallacie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antigonus</hi> being deſired by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the <hi>Cynick</hi> to beſtow on him a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19937:62"/>Talent, anſwered, that a Talent was more then became a <hi>Cynick</hi> to aske,<note place="margin">Seneca. de Benef. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> being againe thereupon requeſted a penny, he anſwered that a penny was leſſe then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a King to give. A baſe and diſhonourable evaſion, that found a way to beſtow neither; whereas a noble and generous minde might have found a way to have beſtowed both. In the Talent he looked at the <hi>Cynick,</hi> what became him to aske, in the penny at a King; what became him to give: whereas he might have given a Talent as a King, and a penny, as to a beggar, yet both with <hi>decorum</hi> enough,</p>
            <p>I have related the ſtory with <hi>Seneca's</hi> cenſure, with which though I will not croſſe, yet thus much of true morality will <hi>Seneca</hi> himſelf grant me, at leaſt in one part of this reply: <hi>that any thing may not be requeſted, but that there is a neceſſary decorum in all our deſires.</hi> A monſtrous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19937:62"/>anſwers it ſelfe. <hi>Eàdem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate negatur quâ petitur.</hi> He gives me a good reaſon to deny him, who hath no reaſon in his requeſt, and indeed that man hath forgot the firſt ground of Charitie, whoſe almes beggar him ſelfe; who by building an Hoſpitall makes himſelfe a fit gueſt to live in it.</p>
            <p>Aske therefore of thy friend but onely that, which thou maiſt aske without a bluſh, and he give without a ſtraine, elſe hath he both, for colourable excuſes for thy deniall. What reaſon hath he to beſtow that which thou haſt no reaſon to demand? Indeed thoſe requeſts are eaſily granted, that bring the bloud into the cheeke neither of the asker, nor giver, not in the one, by the ſtraine of his modeſtie, nor of the other, by ſtraining his abilitie.</p>
            <p>Importunitie and impudence is the baſeneſſe of beggery,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19937:63"/>which elſe may be liberall, while it is asking, if it expreſſe as well a care of his eſtate from whom thou askeſt, as his for whom, to which the eaſineſſe of thy requeſt would offer no violence, whileſt for thy ſelfe thou canſt ſay with <hi>Lot, is it not a little one, and is it not a very little one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But otherwiſe thou teacheſt him a juſt deniall, who makeſt thine owne ſupply anothers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. Be not therefore too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate in thy demands. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie is a civill robbery, if thou be importunate, let it be in anothers ſuperfluitie, leſt whiles thou pulleſt his coate to cover thine owne, thou diſcover his nakedneſſe.</p>
            <p>And as betwixt man and man, ſo towards <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, our petitions are taught a modeſtie in this example.<note place="margin">Matth. 20.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>To ſit on Gods right hand and left,</hi> was a requeſt of more zeale then diſcretion, and therefore found with our
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19937:63"/>Saviour an anſwer rather of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe then grant.</p>
            <p>We may not aske any thing of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, that were to make the power of <hi>God</hi> familiar, and therefore miracles as they are rare things, are as rarely to be asked. 'Tis not for <hi>Gods</hi> ſtate to come every day abroad in his rayes of majeſtie and power: thoſe are things of ſtate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for ſolemne dayes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. And therefore miracles which are effects of <hi>Gods</hi> extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary power, and a kinde of new creation, are things from which <hi>God</hi> reſted the ſeventh day, unleſſe ſome great and generall occaſion be offered.</p>
            <p>By the way therefore, for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Exorciſts</hi> (thoſe <hi>religious conjurers</hi>) that make it but every dayes worke to caſt out devils, that have him at command, as ready as if he were but their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant at will, it is to be feared they will be ſome of thoſe that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19937:64"/>pleading, <hi>did not we caſt out devils in thy Name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 7.22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>and in thy Name doe many wondrous workes?</hi> It ſhall be anſwered, <hi>Away from me ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquity, I know you not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, our deſires muſt not be meaſured at the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Gods</hi> power: we ought rather to weigh with a well-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplined modeſty, what we may aske, not what <hi>God</hi> can give.</p>
            <p>And thus having done with the <hi>probability</hi> of this argument, which as it regarded himſelfe, may ſeeme good and allowable, I come to the <hi>fallacy</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This City is neere, and it is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the intention of which words, might be involved a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold object:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gods Power,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>or, <hi>Gods Juſtice.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt <hi>his Power,</hi> and then would the force of the argument depend upon this ground. That
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19937:64"/>a thing of no great difficulty may eaſily be granted. It's but a ſmall matter for me to aske or <hi>thee</hi> to grant.</p>
            <p>But then would the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be odious in a ſuppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ground, that any thing were hard or eaſie to God, whereas this is only ſo, in a finite and meaſuredſtrength. The <hi>infinitude and immeaſurable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods Power,</hi> knowes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that hath any the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of reſiſtance. What <hi>be</hi> can do (that is, all things) <hi>he</hi> can do eaſily. For <hi>who hath reſiſted his power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 9.19.</note> Rom. 9.19. All things are ſwallowed up in this vaſtnes, <hi>he</hi> is able to do all things with the ſame eaſe, the ſame ſtrength: as eaſily move the earth out of his foundation, as move an atome of duſt, or the leaſt graine of ſand: the ſturdineſſe of the oake is as plyant as the bul-ruſh, with the breath of his mouth. And indeed difficulty is but the taske of a finite ſtrength: ariſing from the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19937:65"/>
               <hi>reſiſtance of the object,</hi> when a thing is accompliſhed, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with <hi>danger,</hi> many times with <hi>paine,</hi> and alwayes with <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</hi> To <hi>God</hi> there is no ſuch thing as difficulty, paine, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. By what ſhould any thing reſiſt him? All reſiſtance is <hi>a contrario,</hi> but to <hi>God all things are ſubordinate,</hi> acted by him, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, moving in him, <hi>and having their being from him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.25 28.</note> How then can any thing move againſt him? To give any thing that power that it could reſiſt <hi>God,</hi> were to make it <hi>God.</hi> But to <hi>him, dictum, factum, ſaid and done</hi> are all one. <hi>He ſpake, and it was done, be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 33.9.</note> 
               <hi>and it ſtood faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this firſt ſenſe of the words, I paſſe by, as thinking it not ſo properly the meaning of the words, &amp; come to the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, made of the <hi>ſecond object, Gods Justice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And if it be ſo underſtood, then would it be of a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſenſe: as if he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19937:65"/>indeed, that this <hi>Bela,</hi> or here <hi>Zoar,</hi> did indeed juſtly deſerve as it had partaken in a ſhare of the ſame ſinnes, ſo to partake in the community of the ſame puniſhment. But yet it's but <hi>a little City,</hi> and the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants but few; what if then for <hi>my ſake,</hi> ſo <hi>ſmall a City,</hi> and ſuch an handfull of men be exempted? Would that be any breach of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> or any taske of <hi>Gods</hi> impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall dealing, if of ten thouſand ten ſhould be ſpared? Would ſuch an inch breake any ſquare, ſo ſmall a matter be ſtuck at, upon my deſire, for my ſafety? Spare it then, <hi>O Lord, 'tis but a litle one, nonne perexigua eſt?</hi> ſo exceeding <hi>little,</hi> that to pardon and paſſe by it, can no way impeach thy Juſtice; which ſhall acquit it ſelfe well enough, in that number which ſhall juſtly feele it's juſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, and as to that number that ſhall in thine anger ſuffer, theſe I ſue for, loſe all proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19937:66"/>and become no number? ſo this act of thy mercy being ſet, by that exemplary act of thy Juſtice, ſhall eſcape all notice &amp; cenſure.</p>
            <p>Were I but guilty of a little <hi>oratory,</hi> I am perſwaded, ſome might eaſily be cozen'd into a beliefe, that the argument were very ſolid, and would well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough hold water.</p>
            <p>What? (ſaies naturall reaſon, and unchriſtened Juſtice) have I rigidly obſerv'd all thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements <hi>from my youth hitherto?</hi> have I juſtled counter againſt the world,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.20</note> neglected (out of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and godly feare) my profits, my pleaſures, my humors, borne the obloquies and frequent ſcornes of the multitude; and ſhall not a <hi>little ſin, a ſmall erro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> be excuſed in me?</p>
            <p>Is not this a frequent plea, that not only the formall worldling, but even Gods ſervants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves make, and wherein they are wonderfully pleas'd? as if (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth)
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19937:66"/>they had well accquitted themſelves, if they have beene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in their callings, or the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of religion; O then a little ſlacking, one neglect or ommiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may well enough be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo ſin in the crowde of their vertues paſſe unſeene, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſured.</p>
            <p>So goodneſſe muſt be a ſtale to ſinne, and diligence the patrones, at leaſt of a ſmall neglect! As if by doing well we purchaſed a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to do ill, and that we might deale with God as the <hi>Romane ſlaves</hi> did with their <hi>maſters,</hi> who having ſerv'd them all the reſt of the yeere, yet for onſt (at the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnals</hi>) their <hi>maſters</hi> ſerved them:<note place="margin">Macrobius.</note> ſo here, as if (forſooth) becauſe we have done <hi>God</hi> (as we thinke) reaſonable good ſervice, and beene indifferently diligent in our callings, <hi>God</hi> muſt therefore onſt, or ſo ſerve us, authorize us to ſin a little, and excuſe us for a little when we have ſinned.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:19937:67"/>
            <p>Is not this almoſt to make <hi>God</hi> the author of ſin, and goodneſſe monſtrouſly to father her owne contrary? Would you not thinke it a monſtrous madneſſe, and ſtrange ſoloeciſme, if a maſter ſhould aske his ſervant why he had offended in this or that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and he ſhould reply, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am thy ſervant, or becauſe I have ſerved thee well and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in other things? Would you not think this ſervant mad? And would you not thinke that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that would accept this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for a ſufficient excuſe, more mad and fooliſh than t'other? Yet juſt ſo do we deale with God. Why have we beene bold in this or that matter to offend? for onſt to omit this or that duty, a little too ſlack of our diligence? becauſe (forſooth) we are <hi>his</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, becauſe we have heretoforé beene officious and zealous. What a ſtrange reaſon is here, we are bad becauſe we have beene good?</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:19937:67"/>
            <p n="2">2. As in this monſtrouſly we would make <hi>God</hi> the author, and goodneſſe the excuſe and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſin, ſo <hi>ſecondly,</hi> it's a thing we never make any bones of, never ſticke at to <hi>ſinne a little, ſo it be but a little,</hi> it occaſion be, to ſtep a little out of the way, ſo that we rove not paſt the outter, moſt <hi>declination ſin's of Zodiack.</hi> Let us go no further, &amp; then, as if there were a <hi>Cancer</hi> on hell's ſide, as there is in heaven, and that we could be <hi>retrograde, returne</hi> when we would, fearleſſe of the ſteep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that aſcent, and unwary of the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne, we ſtop nor, (having begun our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere (without <hi>Gods</hi> great mercy) till we are carried headlong into the vale of death, and plunged in the gulph of eternall miſery.</p>
            <p>O <hi>(my heloved)</hi> take heed of this killing indulgence to your ſelves, to thinke to ſinne a <hi>little,</hi> a little to go aſide, a little out of the pale of <hi>Gods protection.</hi> O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19937:68"/>what thou doſt, no more but give the devill a little hold of thy ſoule, no more but begin'ſt a race from the top and verge of a ſteep hill, no more but teare a little of the writing and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betwixt <hi>God</hi> and thee, no more but adde a little thorne to the crowne of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I am deceived almoſt as much as thou art? thou doſt not theſe a little, but much, and highly, eſpecially if voluntarily thou ſinneſt but thy little.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt, <hi>its a great errour that any finne is little?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, as great a one, <hi>that thou canſt returne, repent, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive thy ſelfe being at a fault, but thy little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>no ſinne is little.</hi> For tell me, what is little? I would faine know, <hi>what is little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is a graine of ſand <hi>little?</hi> Yes, <hi>in compariſon</hi> of a pebble ſtone. But is a graine of ſand <hi>poſitively and abſolutely</hi> little. No? For in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19937:68"/>reſpect of an <hi>atome</hi> it is great; nay, that <hi>atome</hi> is not little nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For if it be <hi>quantitative,</hi> then hath it <hi>extenſion,</hi> if <hi>extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> then <hi>one part without another,</hi> and then, at leaſt <hi>thoſe parts are leſſe then the whole,</hi> and ſo might I diſpute of thoſe <hi>parts,</hi> and the <hi>parts of thoſe parts in infinitum.</hi> I know in regard of <hi>animate bodies,</hi> the beſt <hi>Philoſophers</hi> are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they have their <hi>praefixed termes of magnitude upwards and downewards, their maximum quod ſic,</hi> and <hi>minimum quod non,</hi> their <hi>minimum quod ſic,</hi> and <hi>maximum quod non:</hi> but there is nothing in the whole <hi>univerſe,</hi> that is <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and poſitively little.</hi> And this I affirme not onely <hi>in bodies,</hi> but all <hi>accidents,</hi> whether <hi>quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, actions or whatſoever,</hi> to which in any manner we attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute <hi>quantitie</hi> and the <hi>affections of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tell me then, <hi>what is a little ſinne? Sin</hi> being an <hi>aberration</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:19937:69"/>from the right way, meaſure me the true <hi>diſtance of that aberrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> meaſure me <hi>the line</hi> that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that <hi>distance;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omne quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibile in ſemper divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilia.</note> thou wilt finde a kinde of <hi>infiniteneſſe</hi> in it. <hi>For each line is infinitely diviſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth then is, we call ſome ſinnes little, not that any is <hi>abſolutely and really</hi> ſo, but only <hi>in reſpect of ſome greater.</hi> So that our juſtification in this kinde, would prove but like the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> meerely <hi>comparative:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.11.</note> 
               <hi>I thank God I am not as other men, nor even as this Publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be not then ſo nerre a <hi>papist</hi> in thine opinion, that (as they hold ſome <hi>ſinnes veniall</hi>) thon as abſurdly holdſt ſome ſinnes <hi>little,</hi> or the <hi>Phariſees</hi> that hold ſome of <hi>Gods commands to be but little ones. Matth.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Be not deceived</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>for becauſe of theſe things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.6.3, 4, 5.</note> what things? <hi>Eph. 5.6.</hi> Sinnes which the world eſteemes but little of <hi>fornication,</hi> called but a trick of youth, all <hi>unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19937:69"/>covetouſneſſe,</hi> nay he names leſſe yet, <hi>filthineſſe fooliſh talking, jeſting,</hi> even <hi>for theſe things: let no man deceive you with vaine words,</hi> as if theſe were but <hi>little,</hi> petty trifles of ſinne, toyes, not worth the heeding, for whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, how light ſoever you may thinke of them,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>even for theſe things cometh the wrath of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the children of diſobedience: be not therefore partakers with them.</hi> And indeed, they that upon this plea, are bold to commit any ſin, argue more in it their owne ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cineſſe, then the ſins excuſe.</p>
            <p>It is not proper, nor probable that an offender will rightly judge of the qualitie of his own fault. He muſt cenſure of it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom it was committed.</p>
            <p>What was (in it ſelfe) the <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of an apple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 36.</note> what the <hi>gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a few ſticks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 15.32.</note> or the <hi>uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Arke when it was ſo ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 6.6.</note> that it ſeemed in danger of falling? What can we thinke of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19937:70"/>theſe, which might ſeeme each one to have a good plea, the firſt of <hi>wiſedome,</hi> the ſecond <hi>neceſſitie,</hi> the third <hi>pietie?</hi> Were not theſe ſmall matters, and if ſinnes very little ones? and yet the leaſt of theſe little ones, coſt no leſſe then death,<note place="margin">Gen 2.17. Num. 15.36.</note> at leaſt tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and ſtretched in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the merit of an eternall.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.7.</note> Take heed in theſe things of <hi>charging God fooliſhly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the earth doe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly. Gen.</hi> 18.25. Yet if our captious wiſedomes have not learned ſo much Chriſtian mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to be controuled by this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but that they dare think hardly of it, and ſpeake it in the place of <hi>extreame juſtice:</hi> reaſon it ſelfe may file into a ſmoother phraſe, the roughneſſe of that word, and Chriſten it <hi>a most lawfull and juſt ſeveritie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eadem ratio rotunditatis in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jore &amp; in minore circulo, ſic &amp; in peccato,</hi> there is the ſame kinde
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:19937:70"/>of roundneſſe in a greater or leſſe circle, ſo is there the ſame kinde of obliquity in the greater and leſſe ſinne. A little thing is little, but then unfaithfulneſſe in a little is a great fault.<note place="margin">Num. 15.</note> 
               <hi>The gathering of thoſe ſtickes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.2 Sam 6.</note> 
               <hi>the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that apple, the touching of the Arke,</hi> were <hi>in them ſelves but little things,</hi> but then the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in theſe littles was no ſmall fault. God commanded, and his command (which is the bond of all our obedience) was broken, and therefore what ever the things were, for weake and ſinfull man, with neglect of ſo many great and ſtrong oblige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to offend <hi>an infinite and omnipotent majeſtie,</hi> makes theſe little ſinnes of ſo great a guilt, that as no man without in juſtice can excuſe their ſinnes, much leſſe with any juſtice can any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their puniſhments.</p>
            <p>But (let me name it truely) it is a kinde of generall <hi>Atheiſme,</hi>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:19937:71"/>in this declining age (out of the greater acquaintance in ſinne) that they dare with boldneſſe act thoſe things againſt <hi>God,</hi> and eſteeme them but little, which (if done againſt a King, nay farre inferiour men) would be judged, by common civilitie, impudently abſurd, and monſtrous. And no marvell, if to <hi>Atheiſme</hi> be added impudence, in thoſe <hi>who knowing that there is a God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>doe yet in their workes deny him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> I have ſhewed the firſt deceit, of men that thinke ſome ſinnes little, the ſecond followes (as bad as the firſt) <hi>that men having offended but a little, can eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them ſelves.</hi> Let them doe this or that, either for experience or curioſitie, or company, or gaine, or pleaſure, or the like, without faile they will goe no further, the devill ſhall in vaine expect a further progreſſe, into any further degrees of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Thou foole! is repentance a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19937:71"/>worke of thine own? or if not, why wilt thou promiſe ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, that which is not in thy power? Thou wilt <hi>ſinne a little</hi> but ſurely returne. To ſin is in thine own power, but that thou <hi>repent</hi> is in the power and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>God onely.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim, 2.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Alack vaine man! with how little reaſon doſt thou flatter thy vaine hope? Canſt thou leap off a ſteep rock, and thinke to ſtop in the middle way, when thou art carried headlong <hi>impotente ſui pondere,</hi> with a weight and ſwing unable to manage or controwle it ſelfe?<note place="margin">2 Sam 14.14.</note> Canſt thou <hi>ſpill water on the ground</hi> and thinke to gather it up, or put fire to towe, and hope it will not riſe into aflame?</p>
            <p>O thou little knoweſt the fruitfulneſſe of ſinne, the prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and inclination of thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the juſtice of God, that often puniſhes one ſin with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Ninus</hi> his victorie,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:19937:72"/>
               <hi>prior quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> victoria cauſa ſequentis erat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iustin. hiſt. lib. 1.</note> every former victory occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the following: and moſt true it is of ſinne, that every firſt makes way for the next, and he that makes no conſcience to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the one, will make leſſe to commit a ſecond, and yet leſſe of the third. For as each <hi>act</hi> of ſin ſtaines the ſoule, ſo it gets <hi>an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination</hi> and <hi>diſpoſition to further acts,</hi> by which is wrought <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> and by <hi>cuſtome neceſſity.</hi> As S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">Auguſtinè.</note> 
               <hi>Dum ſervitur libidini, facta eſt conſuetudo, dum conſuetudini non reſiſtitur, inducta eſt neceſſitas,</hi> ſo that at the laſt, by this <hi>fatall gradation</hi> men a rive at the height and impudence of ſinning, from which (without <hi>Gods</hi> great mercie) there is never a returne,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.27.</note> 
               <hi>but a fearefull looking for of judgment, and fiery indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which ſhall devoure the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yeild not therefore to any the leaſt ſin, let not the infancie of it
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:19937:72"/>flatter thee, though it ſmile up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee with a childiſh inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and pretend nought but harmeleſſe ſimplicitie, for here, in a true (though differing) ſence, may I uſe the words of the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.9.</note> 
               <hi>happy ſhall he be that taketh and daſheth theſe little ones against the ſtones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was but a <hi>little cloud</hi> at firſt,<note place="margin">1 Kin. 18. 44, 45.</note> that afterwards overcaſt the whole heaven, ſo a little ſin, (if not ſcattered by the ſacred power of <hi>the bleſſed Spirit</hi>) will hide all the heaven from us, eclipſe the light of <hi>Gods countenance,</hi> and at laſt involue us in eternall dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And as that <hi>little cloud</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came at length a daſhing ſhower, the <hi>leaſt of graines,</hi> in its growth, becomes one of the greateſt ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; <hi>Agraine of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13.31.</note> 
               <hi>which is indeed the leaſt of all ſeeds when it is ſowne, but when it is growne up, is the greateſt amongſt herbs, ſo that the fowles of the ayre, come and lodge in the branches
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19937:73"/>thereof. Matth.</hi> 13.31. ſuch is the increaſe and growth of ſin.</p>
            <p>Believe not then the devill and thine own deceitfull heart: they are importunate with thee. What! wilt thou deny them <hi>a little? ſo little?</hi> ſuch a trifle? not grant ſo much roome in thine heart as to ſow <hi>one of the leaſt graines?</hi> Why wilt thou be thus fool'd, and couzened out of thy ſoule? Looke whether tends the devils modeſty. If he ſhould ſay to thee downright, bluntly, and without more adoe, <hi>give me thy ſoule,</hi> he would ſtartle as well thy courage, as awake thy vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancie: and becauſe he does not ſo (knowing then he ſhould he ſure to be denied) wilt thou be the more careleſſe, becauſe he is the more cunning? Why; beleeve it, he askes as much in <hi>a poriphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis:</hi> now he askes thee, but this thy little; he askes thy ſoule, and aymes (though he ſeeme to play at ſmall games) indeed at thy
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:19937:73"/>whole ſtock. He askes thy ſoule, but more ſlyly, leaſt thou ſhouldſt deny him. And therefore, thou oughteſt to be the more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, againſt his cheating mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, by how much there's the more reall danger in his ſeeming leſſe deſire. It is ſo farre from any care of thee, that it is indeed but a cunning tolling of thee on, by a ſeeming careleſſeneſſe, and the innocence of a little ſinne. For know undoubtedly, that of theſe littles is made the <hi>devils skrew,</hi> and <hi>the ſtaires that lead to bell are winding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nemo repentè fit turpiſſimus</hi> — No man at onſt jumps into the extremity of ſin,<note place="margin">Invenal. Sat. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of hell (like that of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) <hi>commeth not with obſervation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 17.20.</note> but by an inſenſible progreſſe, we goe downeward, and therefore are bid <hi>to remember from whence we are falne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev 2.5.</note> and <hi>the ſervants</hi> come to their Lord with wonder in their mouthes,<note place="margin">Matth. 13.27.</note> 
               <hi>Maſter didſt not
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:19937:74"/>thou ſow good ſeed in thy field, from whence then hath it tares?</hi> It e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcap't their notice for a long while, even till the blade ſprung up and the fruit appeared.</p>
            <p>Thou ſeeſt, here it is wiſedome to be a preciſian, and that a nice and tender conſcience, is the <hi>beſt antidote</hi> againſt ſecretly <hi>inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting poyſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had <hi>David</hi> before <hi>made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with his eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 31.1.</note> he had not ſo neerely unmade his covenant with his <hi>God;</hi> when he beheld <hi>Bathſheba</hi> from his tarras.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.13.17.</note> Little thought <hi>David</hi> that little thiefe, <hi>lust</hi> (that through the windowes of his eyes ſtole into his heart) ſhould have opened the doore to thoſe two great ſinnes <hi>adultery</hi> and <hi>murther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.9.</note> Little thought he, the fruitfulneſſe of that ſinne of luſt, would for one infant, have doublely loſt a man, firſt in drink and then in bloud.</p>
            <p>Little thought <hi>Peter</hi> (when he ment at firſt,<note place="margin">Mark. 14.66, 67. &amp;c.</note> with a plaine deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:19937:74"/>handſomely to have ſhitted of the dangerous <hi>inquiſition</hi>) to 01 have runne into oaths and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations. By ſtepping but aſide, he little thought to have run ſo farre from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> even further then they that <hi>before forſooke him and fled</hi> from him.<note place="margin">Matth. 26.56.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee then, how one ſinne uſhers an other, and like <hi>one wave cals another, till at last the deepe waters goe over thy ſoule.</hi> Canſt thou pull one linke of a chaine and thinke the reſt will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? In that little ſin thou art <hi>dejectus de ſtatu &amp; gradu,</hi> diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and diſordered in thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, ſo that thine enemie may cloſe with thee. Such is the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and improvement of ſin!</p>
            <p>Since then, it is ſins method, to winne upon us by little and little, here a ſnatch and there, let us <hi>be wiſe as ſerpents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.16.</note> and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine againſt the policy of that <hi>grand ſerpent.</hi> Let us arme our ſelves with a ſacred jealouſie, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19937:75"/>well wrought reſolution, which as Satan in vaine by force, at onſt ſhould attempt to breake, let us take heed, that he never by his policie unravell,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> and as <hi>Seneca</hi> counſells, <hi>nobis quia regredi non eſt facile, optimum eſt non progredi,</hi> becauſe we cannot eaſily return, 'its beſt way not to goe forward.</p>
            <p>I have thus farre inſiſted out this argument of <hi>Lots</hi> in a <hi>three fold ſenſe naturall, morrall, and theologicall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>in way of eſſay,</hi> I inquired into the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why men are naturally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate, and indulgent to little things. Secondly I inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, what this is which we call <hi>little,</hi> and whether i: <hi>import any eſſence or quiddity, poſitive and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute,</hi> or onely <hi>comparative and of relation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>morall</hi> ſenſe of the words, I endevoured by ſome <hi>Ethicall</hi> precepts, to ſtop the voracitie and greedineſſe of our deſires,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19937:75"/>both to <hi>God</hi> and man; to cure men of that wolfe and to traine them up unto a diſcreet modeſty, in all requeſts, that what we aske may be without a bluſh, and given without a ſtraine, which will then be, when like <hi>Lot</hi> of his <hi>Zoar</hi> we can ſay for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, <hi>it is a little one, and nonne perexigua eſt, is it not a very little one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Theologicall ſenſe</hi> I have ſhewed might be twofold, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of a <hi>twofold object</hi> that may be ſuppoſed <hi>Gods power,</hi> or <hi>His juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>His power,</hi> and then would the words involue an errour as dangerous as popular, <hi>viz.</hi> that any thing were eaſier or harder to <hi>God,</hi> whereas this is ſo onely in a meaſured and finite ſtrength. <hi>It is a little one</hi> is a good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in that it implies our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, but <hi>it is a little one</hi> is a bad argument if it looke at <hi>Gods</hi> power.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:19937:76"/>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſecond ſenſe</hi> (ſuppoſing the <hi>ſecond object,</hi> which is <hi>Gods juſtice</hi>) is likewiſe dangerous, as confeſſing that <hi>Bela</hi> or <hi>Zoar</hi> (a Citie of the plaines of <hi>Sodom</hi>) doth partake with the reſt of the Cities in the communitie of the ſame ſinnes, but it is but a little Citie, and <hi>Gods juſtice</hi> cannot be impeached, as partiall in ſparing ſo few men, ſo little a Citie.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have proceeded, and though perhaps I have made much adoe about a little, yet I am unwilling to let goe the ſame <hi>theme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who will not there moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, where he knowes his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie will make the greateſt bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery? It is this way, and almoſt this way onely, the devill winnes upon us. <hi>The Serpent</hi> thus <hi>by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little windes</hi> himſelfe in. He never delt with any except <hi>our Saviour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth 4.6.</note> to bid him, <hi>caſt down himſelfe from the higheſt pinacle of the Temple:</hi> it is his wont to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:19937:76"/>us, to cozen us by degrees, from the height of our zeal and vertue, as by winding ſtayres, and this way he's ſo much the more like to obtaine his end, by how much we are leſſe able to diſcerne ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the declination or danger of the way.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt vented a <hi>paradox,</hi> and yet though I call it ſo, I will adventure to expoſe it to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of your cenſure, and am much deceived if it be not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for more than halfe a truth; and this it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Little ſinnes, or thoſe ſins which we take for little ones, are many times of greater guilt and danger, than thoſe which we eſteeme great ones.</hi> Be pleaſed to ſuſpend your cenſure, till I acquaint you with two or three reaſons.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt they are committed in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> greater <hi>numbers,</hi> and ſo <hi>numero ſi non pondere valent,</hi> their number will weigh againſt the others weight. The <hi>fruit of this forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:19937:77"/>tree</hi> growes, if not great in bulke, yet in branches and clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> they are done with greater boldneſſe, and <hi>holdneſſe is the very formale</hi> of a ſinne, that which dies in the deepeſt guilt, and aggravates it beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, as if (forſooth) by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſome extraordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with <hi>God,</hi> we might be borne out in a little boldneſſe, and (as the fooliſh mouſe plaid with the Lions beard) expect that his patience ſhould ſtill ſleep though we <hi>tempt it every day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.12.</note> with the ſaucie importunity of theſe childiſh and ſportfull ſins.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> thoſe ſins men call lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, are ſeldome repented of, and what wonder (when committed with ſo much careleſneſſe) if they be omitted in our repentance. <hi>Poſſunt verba dare &amp; evadere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilla mala, ingentibus obviam itur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> they are cauſes of greater: and thereupon much
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:19937:77"/>of that guilt, which is in the ſins which follow in upon theſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones, may be transferred back againe upon thoſe, without whoſe treachery they had never come in. And though by a <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> neceſſity they produce not theſe ſucceeding effects yet by an inclining (nay tempting) diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they open the gap too, and draw in a whole huddle of ſins, and thoſe many times great ones.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Examples are of this but too frequent. Have we entred a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle way into any unlawfull courſe, and do we not often find more deſperate courage to wade through, than modeſty to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, or repentance to go back? <hi>Over ſhooes, over boots: we are in, and cannot be much worſe,</hi> or if we be, <hi>its as good on a little further, and repent for altogether.</hi> There's but <hi>a broken piece of a day or eſtate left, I can do no great good with that: as good throw the helve after the hatchet.</hi> Thus (in thoſe and ſuch
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:19937:78"/>like of the <hi>devils Apothegms</hi>) we encourage our ſelves from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſinne, making that a ſpur which ſhould be a bridle, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging our ſelves by the infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this argument, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulphe our ſelves into an irrevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable condition. Tuſh! <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is but a ſneaking and poore conditioned vertue, as good on, and ſecure ſin with ſin.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe there is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable example in <hi>Seneca,</hi> of one <hi>Piſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca de Ira, lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a Romane Generall,</hi> a man moſt unfitting that rule, who was (to tyranny) ruled by his owne paſſions.</p>
            <p>Two ſouldiers having gone together out of the Campe, and one only returning, <hi>Piſo</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes him that returned, as preſuming him guilty of his <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades</hi> death. In vaine doth the poore man crave any mercy, who is denied the juſt triall of his owne innocence, in the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpit. Away he is hal'd to the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:19937:78"/>block, where with his necke out ſtretcht, ready to receive the fatal blow, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behold fortune (more kinde to him than that tyrant) preſents him with the ſight of his fellow, juſt now upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. With mutuall embraces, and the joyfull acclamations of the army, both are brought to <hi>Piſo's</hi> Tent, that he may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the ſouldiers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, and his owne miſtake. But what? muſt a great generall, and that in the ſight of all his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, acknowledge in his acquitall, that he could be unjuſt? It ſhall be proved juſt, becauſe he will not repent, which rather than he will do, he will ſinne mature<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and deſperately, to prove he did not offend ſo much as raſhly. <hi>Piſo</hi> will now, rather than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit one, condemne both, both him that had not, and him that was not murthered; ſo that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one did appeare innocent, two muſt periſh: nay <hi>Piſo</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:19937:79"/>a third yet, the <hi>Centurion.</hi> And wot you the wit of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to finde juſt cauſe for all? Thee (ſaith he) I condemne to execution, becauſe thou waſt condemned: <hi>thee,</hi> becauſe by thine abſence, thou waſt the cauſe of his condemning: and thee, the <hi>Centurion,</hi> becauſe being commanded to execute him whom I condemned, thou diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyedſt my command. <hi>Excogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) <hi>quemadmodum tria crimina faceret, quia nullum invenerat,</hi> he found a way &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In dealing of which ſort, of ſtrengthening and ſeaming one ſinne with another, we deale like a wiſe Counſellor of the <hi>Duke of Florence,</hi> who (having a great heap of dirt and rubbiſh, which without great labour, and much expence could not be conveyed away) was by a grave <hi>Senater</hi> moſt politickly adviſed, to dig a gaeat hole in the ſame place, and bury it in that. But (replied the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:19937:79"/>
               <hi>Duke</hi>) where ſhall that earth which is digged out of the pit be beſtowed? (Why? ſayes the <hi>eight of the wiſe men</hi>) make the hole ſo much the deeper, and bury both.</p>
            <p>Make the tale a <hi>fable,</hi> and laugh (in the <hi>morall</hi>) at thine owne folly, thou that thinkeſt in what kinde ſoever to hide one ſin with another:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 11.13.17.</note> as <hi>David</hi> adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with drunkenneſſe,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.9.</note> both with murther:<note place="margin">Mar 14 66 67, &amp;c. 71.</note> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſimple de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of his <hi>Lord</hi> with curſing and forſwearing, or (as uſually the cuſtome of many is) to hide any offence with lying or ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp;c. Thou haſt digged a pit,<note place="margin">Pſa. 139.8</note> ſay <hi>as deep as hell</hi> (for thither art thou going) to hide thy firſt ſin, yet indeed in this more foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh than him I ſpake of. But ſuppoſe it hid; where ſhall the ſecond be hid? make a deeper pit. Thou maiſt go to hell that way, but never hide thy ſin from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>even there alſo ſhall thine hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 139.10</note> 
               <hi>and thy right hand finde</hi> ſuch out.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:19937:80"/>
            <p>Reſolve then, thou canſt not hide, much leſſe ſecure one ſin by adding more: thou thinkeſt to bury the firſt ſinne in the ſecond, but where ſhall the ſecond be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried? How ridiculous is this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of men, yet how often pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed? <hi>David</hi> himſelfe (as I ſaid) had this gull put upon him. He committed adultery, to rid a way and bury this filth, he is guilty of drunkenneſſe, and finding this pit yet too little, he will wiſely dig deeper, and go neerer hell yet, in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riab's</hi> murther: but fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the vaine policie of it, and that this way the maſſe of his dung-hill did but riſe to greater bulke (like the <hi>Augean ſtables</hi>) his only way was by the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant teares of repentance (as by an <hi>Alpheus</hi>) to purge away that corrupted maſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> was thus ſerv'd too. He thought at firſt, but with a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome conveyance of his body, to have ſhifted off the blow he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:19937:80"/>But this little motion carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with ſuch a ſwinge, that he ran further from our <hi>Saviour</hi> then the reſt that fled:<note place="margin">Mar. 14.71</note> he ſwears &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweares,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.61</note> ſo that had not our <hi>Lord lookt back to</hi> recal him, he had run eternally away from him.</p>
            <p>Do not theſe examples preach unto you ſtrict vigilancy, yea and preciſeneſſe over your waies, that you offend not, though never ſo little, that you gratifie not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill with the leaſt ſin. Thou ſeeſt of what dangerous conſequence and fruitfull improvement ſin is: give him not one linke, by pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that, all the whole chaine will follow.<note place="margin">Luk. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 22, 23.</note> Let not in then this enemy, whom thou mayeſt eaſily at firſt keep out, and who (being onſt admitted in) will be too ſtrong for thee.</p>
            <p>I have done with this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I have longer inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted on, becauſe it is the ſtrength and thigh of his requeſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.25.31.</note> but I have touched it in the hollow of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:19937:81"/>it, and therefore you can expect no other, but that <hi>the requeſt</hi> muſt <hi>come in halting,</hi> which followes in theſe words, <hi>O let me eſcape thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> But before I paſſe to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and laſt argument, here ſtands in a <hi>parentheſis</hi> a paſſionate <hi>Epanalepſis,</hi> ſet downe by way of <hi>interrogation [is it not a little one?]</hi> In which having done with the <hi>matter</hi> of the words, the <hi>Rhetorick</hi> only is left to our obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a little one, O let me eſcape thither, and is it not a little one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words (methinkes) I finde, as ſomewhat of paſſion, ſo much of a compaſſionate indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſo that I know not what more winning, and affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moving, could have been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. A right piece of true <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> that woes the affections like a right artiſt, like one that would derive both <hi>powerfull and patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> into his <hi>auditory</hi> his owne <hi>notions,</hi> his owne <hi>ſence,</hi> and like a <hi>common Genius</hi> of the whole
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:19937:81"/>body, <hi>animate</hi> the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with one and the ſame <hi>ſoul.</hi> This is the true end of all <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> both <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>ſacred, ducere affectus,</hi> to take and lead the affections, <hi>quoquo velis,</hi> which ſoever way you pleaſe. And to doe that, is there any way but through the underſtanding?</p>
            <p>Which being truely and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſo, I can but wonder (for underſtand I doe not) what end they have propoſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whoſe preaching is more affectedly obſcure then <hi>Delphian Oracles, or Egyptian Ieroglyphicks:</hi> that indeed make good in a bad ſence, that of the <hi>Apostle</hi> that calls <hi>preaching propheſying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14: 3.</note> 
               <hi>that have mouthes,</hi> nay words, <hi>and ſpeak not,</hi> and would make good that curſe upon their auditors, to be of thoſe, that <hi>hearing heare and underſtand not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 6 9. 82</note> 
               <hi>and ſeeing ſee and perceive not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 28.26.</note> And indeed I wonder at the patience of them that heare ſuch, who are delt with
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:19937:82"/>as the <hi>Foxe</hi> did with the ſtorke. Who inviting the ſtorke to a feaſt, powr'd his liquor into ſo ſlat and ſhallow a diſh, that the poor ſtork was only a ſpectator, (while the Fox lapt up the meat) his long bill being unable to dip in that ſhallow platter. For you that heare ſuch, I know not (in that regard) what you looſe if you ſleep whilſt ſuch preach, for if they will not make you audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, I know not, why you ſhould (in the <hi>Church</hi>) onely be ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. But for ſuch Preachers, I would upon the pardon of a <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> give them (I think) good counſell. What need they labour an houre, not to be underſtood? Is it not a more compendious way (if they would not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) to ſay nothing?</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is an other ſort, that on the contrary, as the former make preaching propheſying, ſo theſe in as bad ſenſe, would make good that of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of ſome
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:19937:82"/>that call <hi>preaching fooliſhneſſe:</hi> as if becauſe preaching muſt not be <hi>gareiſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.21.23.</note> it muſt therefore be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did. Tis beyond the patience of an underſtanding man, to beare the rankeneſſe of their undigeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meditations; and <hi>God</hi> ſure, but for our puniſhment never made ſuch Ambaſſadors.</p>
            <p>It is beyond both my purpoſe and skill, to preſcribe the beſt way, who acknowledg my ſelfe in the loweſt claſſe of learners. But ſure, there is a latitude, wherein men may both pleaſe and profit, and it will prove beſt, when men learne firſt the <hi>inclination</hi> of their owne <hi>Genius,</hi> and ſeeke to perfect that, whether in the kinde of <hi>proſecution</hi> or <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Much of imitation is diſtort and lame.</p>
            <p>I have with a perfunctory touch done with this, and come to <hi>Lots</hi> affirmative requeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O, let me eſcape thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> preſcribes <hi>Lot</hi> the way to
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:19937:83"/>eſcape, <hi>flye to the mountaine: Lot</hi> replyes, <hi>O not ſo my Lord, for I cannot, &amp;c.</hi> there's a <hi>nè ſic,</hi> of diſobedience, <hi>O not ſo,</hi> and there's a <hi>nè fortè,</hi> that is his diſtruſt, and then, <hi>behold, this Citle is better,</hi> there is confidence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Man's a diſtruſtfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and yet man's a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous creature. For is there any <hi>climax</hi> in ſinne, whoſe higheſt ſtep we have not reached. If the baſeneſſe and abjectedneſſe of our feares ſhrinke us as low as hell, the ſwolne pride and height of our preſumption preaches us as high as heaven: ſo that with a ſaucie preſumption, we dare ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulate and indent with <hi>God,</hi> nay even chalk him out the way, with a <hi>not ſo my Lord,</hi> but <hi>behold</hi> a better conveniency, <hi>O let me eſcape thither;</hi> thither to <hi>Zoar one of the five Cities of the plaines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Man (you ſee) deſires to ſerve <hi>God</hi> eaſily and cheaply, would have the way to heaven
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:19937:83"/>downe the hill, the way broad, ſtrawed with violets and roſes, good ſtore of merry companions along with him, and at the end a wide and open gate, that might be hit blindfold, (O who then would not goe to heaven.) He thinkes it not for the ſtate of <hi>ſo glorious a Palace</hi> to have ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Gate. It's that that offends many, and makes them turne <hi>back againe to Sodom,</hi> that the way ſhould be ſo narrow, ſet with thornes of afflictions, that ſcratch and pull back, a ſolitary and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick way (as many think) through <hi>diſgraces and reproaches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.8. &amp;c.</note> loaden with an <hi>heavy yoake,</hi> an <hi>heavy croſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11.29.</note> that all the way muſt profeſſe patience,<note place="margin">Luk. 9 23.</note> and <hi>invite a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond blow</hi> after the firſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.19.</note> and at the end <hi>agate,</hi> that to get through they muſt creep low as the duſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.39.</note> and ſo <hi>ſtraight</hi> that to get through a man muſt leave his wealth,<note place="margin">Matth. 7.14.</note> his deareſt ſins, nay even his fleſh.</p>
            <p>The Iſraelites way to the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:19937:84"/>Canaan,</hi> is through a <hi>ſea of ſorrow,</hi> made big with their owne teares, that goes high with their owne ſighes, with a ſpirituall <hi>Pharaob</hi> full of rage and at their heeles, through a Wilderneſſe, where there are all things that threaten death and no ſuſtenance for life,<note place="margin">Deut. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>no bread, no water, no fleſh,</hi> no houſes, a long way through deſerts and wilderneſſes, amongſt many <hi>fiery ſerpents,</hi> through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enemies. O theſe are the things that make many a one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe towards <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.39.</note> and goe on <hi>merrily in the wayes of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 7.23.</note> 
               <hi>till a dart ſtrike through his ſoule.</hi> Men will, with much adoe perhaps, be brought to deſire to eſcape the <hi>ſpirituall Sodom,</hi> but not <hi>by the mountaine,</hi> O that's up hill and againſt the haire, but by the way of the <hi>Plaines of Zoar</hi> all would eſcape. O (ſayes every one) let me eſcape but thither, this way, by <hi>Zoar and my ſoule ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:19937:84"/>
            <p>We would be content to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert that petition, <hi>thy will be done on earth as it is in heaven,</hi> to thy will be done in heaven as it is on earth; that our pleaſure might rather be <hi>Gods</hi> ſervice, then Gods ſervice our pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Moſt men deeme the <hi>man in the Goſpel</hi> a foole to buy ſo deare a bargaine, when he found the <hi>Pearle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth, 13.46.</note> that is <hi>to part with all that he had to purchaſe it.</hi> What need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this coſt? without doubt (ſay they) heaven 'may be had at an eaſier rate, and he but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bought his bargaine. Men will take <hi>God</hi> at his word, give him a ſterile and hungry mercie, good words and good wiſhes, but <hi>not ſacrifice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6 6.</note> Good thrifty <hi>Chriſtians</hi> we are growne, that can goe to heaven a cheaper way then by good workes, that's <hi>by the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> we can goe by <hi>faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miſtake me not <hi>(beloved)</hi> as though in this juſt <hi>ſarcaſme.</hi> I tasked in the leaſt wiſe our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:19937:85"/>or befriended in any ſort thoſe unjuſt reproaches and ſcandalls of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> that we ſhould maintaine, that <hi>faith alone without good workes can ſave us,</hi> or that good workes are not at all neceſſary to ſalvation. <hi>Our</hi> doctrine doth more eſtabliſh, yea, and encourage good workes then <hi>theirs,</hi> while it gives them ſo great a valew that the leaſt of them, <hi>even giving a cup of cold water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.42.</note> ſhall be rewarded tenne-thouſand fold above 'its owne worth: <hi>theirs</hi> rewarding them onely after the rate of their own worth.</p>
            <p>I would to <hi>God our</hi> practice were according to our doctrine, and that it were no more the fault of the <hi>men,</hi> then the <hi>religion</hi> ſo to cry up <hi>faith, faith,</hi> that they have cryed downe <hi>good workes,</hi> as if they were <hi>effects of ſuperſtition</hi> and <hi>ignorant zeale.</hi> It is <hi>our</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice not <hi>our</hi> doctrine that ſets faith and good workes at oddes,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:19937:85"/>which are in them ſelves as much connexed and linked as <hi>cauſe and effect, Sunne and light, body and ſhadow,</hi> or what ever example of <hi>ſtrongeſt dependance</hi> can be found in <hi>nature.</hi> But I pray <hi>God</hi> we pay not deare, for thinking to have heaven too cheap.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Epheſians</hi> cryed up <hi>Diana,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19 28.25.27.34.</note> 
               <hi>Diana,</hi> but gaine was in it, gaine was <hi>their godlineſſe,</hi> yea their god. We cry up <hi>faith, faith,</hi> and there is <hi>gaine</hi> in it,<note place="margin">Iam. 2, 24.24.</note> its to exclude <hi>good workes,</hi> thoſe (as if out of faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>Popery</hi>) we have not ſo much pietie (ſhall I ſay?) or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as to keep up thoſe ſtately <hi>edifices</hi> which they built. Nay (I doubt) ſome are ſo farre from putting a finger to the worke, that the repairing of S. <hi>Paul's</hi> is with them <hi>Popiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To finde a neerer way to the <hi>Indies</hi> hath coſt many a life, and to finde a neerer way to heaven, hath coſt many a ſoule. Many a one is in <hi>Sodom</hi> burned, that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:19937:86"/>went to eſcape by <hi>Zoar.</hi> Some will pray, but like ſluggards in their beds, will faſt, but with curious refections;<note place="margin">Prov. 26.14.</note> give almes, but not a moiety of their robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, give a <hi>Vicar</hi> five pounds, and rob the <hi>Church</hi> of five hundred; be temporall <hi>Biſhops</hi> or ſpirituall <hi>Earles;</hi> build an <hi>Hoſpitall</hi> and rob a <hi>Church;</hi> doe good at their deaths, and live how they liſt. Its no wonder there be weavers, and tapſters, and other mechanick <hi>Clergie</hi> if there be temporall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. We will follow <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 9.59.61.</note> but <hi>take leave of our friends first, or bury dead,</hi> but when he <hi>bids us follow,</hi> we will not follow him to the <hi>mountaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to the laſt words and part of my Text, in theſe words, <hi>and my ſoule ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man hath committed in this a foule idolatry, in making the creature a <hi>God,</hi> while before the enjoyment he promiſes all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe (and what not?) in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:19937:86"/>end he propoſes. Man hath done the creature again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as foule an injury, while he vilifies the creature in the enjoyment, as farre as to hate, and loathing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>—<hi>Et concipit aethera mente.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ovid.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O, if we could but compaſſe ſuch a mans eſtate, honour, parts, our deſires ſhould ſit down, we had done for any further wiſhes. But doe we there ſet up our reſt? nay alaſſe are they not either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtfull, or onely the whetters of new appetite? When we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them, how ſhort we fall of that we promiſed from them!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let me eſcape thither and my ſoul ſhall live</hi> (ſaith <hi>Let,</hi>) I have mine hearts wiſh. Was it ſo? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſe he's no ſooner there, but he flyes away from thence to the <hi>mountaine.</hi> So farre ſhort are all outward things in giving a full content!</p>
            <p>We are like the <hi>ſilly ſheapherd</hi> in the <hi>fable,</hi> that ſeeing the <hi>Sunne</hi>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:19937:87"/>as it were on the top of an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looking mountaine, makes haſte up to ſee ſo glorious a thing, but ariving at the top of that, it then appeares on the top of an high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: thither againe his deſire couzens him: with much labour, and freſh hope he arives, it then appeares on a third: and on his third acceſſe, leaves him both now hopeleſſe and weary. He finds to his coſt, it is in heaven he lookes for, and that this is but a fond conceipt, ariſing from his deluded ſenſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Man is this fooliſh ſhepheard,</hi> he lookes upon <hi>honour,</hi> and thinkes happineſſe is there; on <hi>wealth,</hi> that happineſſe is there; on <hi>mirth and pleaſure,</hi> that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is there; to come to theſe with as much paine as promiſe, he labours to arive, in each <hi>object</hi> (like every hill) ſeemes to reſt: thither he arives, ſees it now in another <hi>object:</hi> followes that; it is not there. A new wiſh tempts
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:19937:87"/>him, and that obtain'd deceives him. Alaſſe foole, it is in heaven that thou lookeſt for, <hi>the true Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.</note> 
               <hi>He</hi> onely hath that which thou lookeſt for, in vaine thou lookeſt, <hi>reſt, ſafety, ſecurity, happineſſe in Zoar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 2.25.</note> in that which thy <hi>ſoul haſtes to enjoy,</hi> if thou expect to finde it in <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary</hi> things. There is only reſt to be found <hi>in the mountaine cut out of the rocke, without hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2 34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>which filled the earth, my fills all places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore, if we thinke to eſcape the <hi>ſpirituall Sodom,</hi> go with <hi>David to this mountaine from whence our helpe cometh;</hi> let us go not <hi>by the Plaines,</hi> but (leave to the <hi>papists their Zoar purgatory,</hi> the low way let us goe <hi>via regia,</hi> the high way, the difficultie is abundantly rewarded in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the end.</p>
            <p>Let us then goe on,<note place="margin">Matth. 10.22.</note> and that couragiouſly in the way that <hi>God</hi> hath commanded, and undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:19937:88"/>we ſhall obtaine the end which <hi>God</hi> hath propoſed and promiſed. Say not when <hi>He</hi> bids thee that <hi>I cannot,</hi> 'tis but the weakeneſſe of thy ſloath, not ſtrength that diſinables thee: block not up the way, with the objections of thine owne feares: Diſpence, and that but for a while, with a few, vaine, falſe, and tranſitory pleaſures that would charme thee like <hi>Syrens</hi> in thy way, and then the bitterneſſe of conceited evils is already paſt, thou haſt eſcaped, haſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the height of the <hi>mountaine, where thy ſoul ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19937:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
